<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The liberty of an apostate conscience discovered being a plain narrative of the controversie long depending between Francis Bugg, an officious agent in William Rogers's behalf and quarrel, on the one part, and Samuel Cater and George Smith, prisoners for the testimony of Jesus in Ely goal [sic] on the other part : with their answer to his Painted harlot, &amp;c. ... / published for the information of all friends of truth, and others concerned, and for caution to all such agents as have promoted or spread the late books of Fr. Bugg and W. Rogers.</title>
            <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26770400</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26770400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31338)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1712:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The liberty of an apostate conscience discovered being a plain narrative of the controversie long depending between Francis Bugg, an officious agent in William Rogers's behalf and quarrel, on the one part, and Samuel Cater and George Smith, prisoners for the testimony of Jesus in Ely goal [sic] on the other part : with their answer to his Painted harlot, &amp;c. ... / published for the information of all friends of truth, and others concerned, and for caution to all such agents as have promoted or spread the late books of Fr. Bugg and W. Rogers.</title>
                  <author>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 80, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jo'n Bringhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, defaced, with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Christ Church Library, Oxford University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724? --  Painted-harlot both stript and whipt.</term>
               <term>Cater, Samuel, d. 1711.</term>
               <term>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709.</term>
               <term>Smith, George, --  Quaker.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109781:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>LIBERTY</hi> OF AN Apoſtate Conſcience DISCOVERED: BEING A Plain Narrative of the Controverſie long depending between <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> an officious Agent in <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s Behalf and Quarrel, on the one part: And <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> and <hi>George Smith,</hi> Priſoners for the Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in <hi>Ely</hi> Goal, on the other Part. With <hi>their</hi> Anſwer to <hi>his Painted Harlot, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby <hi>F. B</hi>'s <hi>Liberty of Conſcience is proved</hi> an <hi>Injurious</hi> Bondage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for the Information of all Friends of Truth, and others concerned: and for Caution to all ſuch A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents as have Promoted or Spread the late Books of</hi> Fr. Bugg <hi>and</hi> W. Rogers.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Let no man go beyond or Defraud his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any Matter, becauſe the Lord is the Avenger of all ſuch.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> at the Sign of the Book in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:109781:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109781:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Introduction</hi> TO FRIENDS AND Friendly Readers.</head>
            <p>WHereas my ſelf with others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned have given account of the Unjuſt Actions and Unrighteous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> as hereafter mention'd; This I do ſay, and in the Fear of the Lord teſtifie, that it is not done out of Envy and Ill will to the Man, or to inſult over him, by laying open his Nakedneſs; but do truly deſire his ſincere
<pb facs="tcp:109781:3"/>and unfeigned Repentance, even as we have done ever ſince he began this his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Work; and for that end we have waited long upon him, and have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured much with him; for if wholeſom Advice and Brotherly Admonition could have prevailed with him, to have turned him from his Evil way, which of late Years he hath followed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Narrative and his Malicious Books do plainly ſhew, this had never been: But ſeeing he ſtill followeth his unruly work, and will not be reclaimed to turn from this Evil Spirit which hath led him into theſe things; we do look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves Conſcientiouſly concerned for the Glory of God, and the Honour of his Truth, and alſo for the good of all honeſt and tender People, who have or may have better Thoughts of him than he doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and that ſo under the Profeſſion of Truth, which he in ſome meaſure hath gone under, and may thereby deceive or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray any, and draw them from the peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Truth, into that Spirit with him, into Strife and Contention; which hath been
<pb facs="tcp:109781:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the work he hath followed theſe ſeveral Years, which is the work and fruit of an Evil minded Man; as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>An Evil Man out of the Evil Treaſure of his Heart bringeth forth Evil things.</hi> And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>By the Fruit ye ſhall know them; For Men do not gather Grapes of Thornes, nor Figgs of Thiſtles.</hi> Whereby he ſheweth how impoſſible it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Evil minded Man ſhould bring forth that which is Good.</p>
            <p>And now having given a true and faithful account of the diſorderly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Words and Actions of this Man; I with the reſt concerned with me therein, do leave it and commit it to the juſt Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in all Conſciences, to judge of the wrong he hath done to Truth, to me and others. And whether he hath not iuſtly brought this upon his own Head, ſince we could not prevail with him to forſake his unruly work. And if any be hereafter enſnared hy him and drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide out of the way of the Lord, they muſt
<pb facs="tcp:109781:4"/>bear their own Burden. And I with the reſt concerned in this matter ſhall be clear, in which I reſt, believing God in his own time will clear my Innocency, and more fully manifeſt his guilt, who has abuſed me (and others without any juſt cauſe given him by us) who am a True Friend and Lover of all that truly Love and Fear God, and a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs againſt Envy and Deceit, where ever it doth appear.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ely Priſon,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>17. 12. 1682.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109781:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE LIBERTY OF AN <hi>Apoſtate Conſcience, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis may ſatisfie all into whoſoever Hands it may come, that whereas there is a Differe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce made by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bugg</hi> of <hi>Mildenhall</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk</hi> with <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> of <hi>Little-Port</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Eley;</hi> concerning a Fine, about which the aforeſaid F. B. hath been ſo troubleſome to me &amp; other friends, both in this County &amp; elſewhere which there has been raiſed untrue Reports, and therefore for clearing the Truth, and to ſatisfie all that deſires a right Information of proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, from the beginning thereof, I have therefore taken care, with ſome other Friends, ſo far as they are concerned therein, to give a true Narrative of the Buſineſs from the beginning to this very Day, of the moſt material paſſages; that ſo the Truth being known, it may thereby appear who hath done the wrong in this matter, him, or my ſelf, for which I have been ſo long abuſed by him.</p>
            <p>About the Year <hi>1675,</hi> I being at a Meeting at <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> where <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> dwells; there came one <hi>George Ereind</hi> of <hi>Lakenhoath,</hi> and deſired me to have a Meeting at his Houſe, and before I promiſed him, he being a Stranger to me, and <hi>Francis Bugg</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109781:5"/>being there, I advized with him about it, he having knowledge of the Man; and he told me, that a Meeting would do very well there, and deſired me to go; ſo after I had ſpoke further with the aforeſaid <hi>George Ereind,</hi> and found he deſired the Meeting in a ſerious and weighty conſideration, I found freedom in my ſelf to promiſe him to be at his Houſe the next Day; and alſo told him, he might let his Neighbours know it, and accordingly I went, and <hi>F B.</hi> with me and ſeveral more belonging to <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhall</hi> Meeting, and when we came at the Friends Houſe, there came in ſeveral of his Neighbours; and after ſome time ſpent in waiting upon the Lord, and calling upon his Name in Prayer, I was moved by his Power to ſtand up and declare the Truth to all that were there preſent, in which time whilſt I was ſpeaking, Two Prieſts with ſome other Men, came into the Meeting, and one of thoſe Men that came in with the Prieſts, asked a Man that was in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before, what their Speakers Name was? who ſaid, he did not know; and a Woman Friend ſaid, his Name was written in the Book of Life, where he could not read; then they asked <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> what is your Speakers Name? His anſwer was in the hearing of the Officers and Informers,<note n="*" place="margin">Mark, <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> was Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer here.</note> 
               <hi>HIS NAME IS</hi> SAMUEL CATER, all which time I was declaring the Truth, and no Man asked of me my Name; But after <hi>F. B.</hi> had told it, they all went away, and asked no further after it. As alſo doth appear by this following Certificate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I continued the Meeting until I had cleared my ſelf of what the Lord laid upon me at that time, and then we departed in Peace, being well refreſhed with the Love and Goodneſs of the Lord, whoſe Preſence
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109781:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>was with us to our comfort, yea, and <hi>F. B.</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſaid that he was glad we were there that Day what ever came of it, for we had had a good Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And now whereas <hi>F. B.</hi> or ſome of his Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, have reported that I refuſed to tell my Name at the Meeting; here is a Teſtimony under the Hands of theſe Honeſt Friends that were there preſent.</p>
            <p>FOraſmuch as there hath gone va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reports, relating to a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appointed by <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the knowledge and conſent of <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> and others of us the People called Quakers, held at <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenheath,</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> at the Houſe of one <hi>George Freind,</hi> in or about the Year 1675, which Report goes abroad, as if ſome Perſon or Perſons who came to that meeting with an intent to give Information a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid People then and there met, (as did afterwards appear) did demand of <hi>S. C.</hi> to tell his Name, and that the ſaid <hi>S. C.</hi> did not declare his Name when ſo demanded.</p>
            <p>This is therefore to certifie all into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109781:6"/>whoſe Hands this may come, for the preventing ſuch falſe Reports to paſs for true as much as in us lies; as alſo to clear <hi>S. C.</hi> of the above recited charge againſt him: We whoſe Names are hereunto ſubſcribed, being Eye and Ear Witneſſes to what paſt at the Meeting, do teſtifie, that no Perſon in the aforeſaid Meeting did ask <hi>S. C.</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Name, but one did ask another Man in the aforeſaid Meeting what the Speakers Name was? And he ſaid he did not know; and a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Friend anſwered, his Name was written in the Book of Life where he could not read; then it was asked <hi>F. Bugg</hi> what is your Speakers Name? and <hi>F. B.</hi> anſwered in the hearing of the Officers and Informers, HIS NAME IS SAMUEL CATER, then thoſe that came in as aforeſaid, went out and came into the Meeting no more, leaving <hi>S. C.</hi> declaring the Truth as he was before they came, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109781:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo continued the time they were there, and alſo a conſiderable time after they were gone, after which he concluded the Meeting, and we departed in peace having good unity with <hi>S. C.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible he was enabled by the Power of God, to declare his Truth with an undaunted Spirit in the Face of its Enemies.</p>
            <p>Witneſs our Hands, this 9th Month, 1682.</p>
            <list>
               <item>William Handſhip,</item>
               <item>William Swaits,</item>
               <item>Iohn Maſon,</item>
               <item>Iames Burges,</item>
               <item>Robert Hibble,</item>
               <item>Iohn Burges,</item>
               <item>George Freind,</item>
               <item>Katherine Handſlip,</item>
               <item>Frances Fincham,</item>
               <item>Mary Hogans,</item>
               <item>Henry Hogans.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109781:7"/>
            <p> Now after this it appears, that the Prieſts with ſome others that came with them to the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Informed againſt the meeting to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates who Convicted the meeting, and fined <hi>F. B.</hi> as he ſayes himſelf, Fifteen Pound for me as a Speaker; whoſe Name and Habitation was not known; whenas <hi>F. B.</hi> had told them my Name, and I have cauſe to believe, that the Prieſts, and they which Informed againſt the meeting, were not without Knowledge of the Place of my Habitations if <hi>F. B.</hi> did not tell them, that alſo the Town where I dwell, being but about 10 or 12 computed miles from the place where the meeting was kept: But they having fined <hi>F. B.</hi> for it (as he ſayes) they iſſued out their Warrants, and the Offices diſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for the Fifteen Pound, and he not being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to loſe his Goods, laid down ſo much mony, and kept his Goods by way of an Appeal as he pretended, but never went to Tryal, but gave them his mony for his Fne, being afraid to try his cauſe, leſt he ſhould be Caſt and loſe more Mony to it, as he told me himſelf. Now mark this <hi>F. B</hi>'s proceedings in this matter, he was Fined and Diſtrained, and paid his mony to redeem his Goods; but never told me of it, nor ſpake a word to me about it, until Five or Six Months after, although he had Opportunities e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have done it in that time. Then after I being at London at the Yearly Meeting, <hi>F. B.</hi> came to me to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> meeting, I ſeeing him there, asked him to go with me to the Friends Houſe were I lodged that Night, which he did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when we were in Bed together, he told me he ſuffered a Fine of 15 Pound for me, then I asked him how it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109781:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>was? his Anſwer was, the Magiſtrates had fined him Fifteen Pound, and the Officers took away much Goods for it, ſo he laid down the mony by way of an Appeal, and redeemed his Goods again, and before the time of Tryal he was adviſed by Counſel not to go to Tryal, for there was danger in being Caſt, and that would coſt him more Mony; ſo he did not go on, but deſired the Juſtices that he might withdraw his Appeal, and that they might keep the Mony for his Fine; whereby ſaid he I loſt Fifteen Pound, but I expect thou ſhouldeſt pay me it again, whereat I was ſtrangly ſurprized to hear his demand, to ſee what a ſtrange Temptation had entred the man; then I told him, I ſee no reaſon for that why he ſhould expect it of me, ſeeing he was Fined for his own Teſtimony, for his being at the Meeting, (which he alſo encouraged) and 2dly he paid this mony to ſave his own Goods and not mine. 3dly, he paid it without my conſent or knowledge, neither could I have done it if it had been my own cauſe, and had been Fine my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Neither did I ever pay mony to Prieſt nor other Perſecutors to ſave my ſelf from ſufferings, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I ſuffered for my Teſtimony. And alſo I did look upon this Demand of his, to be unjuſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and therefore I could not in Conſcience pay it: And beſides I then told him, he being far before me as to an Outward Eſta e, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Charity in the caſe to obliege me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and therefore I ſee no juſt or reaſonable cauſe why he ſhould demand any thing of me upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for I was no wayes the cauſe of his being Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, more then any other faithfull Friends muſt have been that miniſters if they had been there; then he ſaid he ſuffered for my not telling my Name my ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109781:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I told him, for that he was to blame and not I,<note place="margin">☞</note> for being ſo forward to tell my Name, he prevented the Officers of asking me, whereby I had not an opportunity to tell them, for after he had told them they went away and never asked me; for if they had, I am ſure I had told them, for it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my practice, both before and after that in the like cauſe, which is well known both to him and other Friends where I have travelled ſince this Act hath been in force: Then he told me if I counted his Demand to be unreaſonable, he would put it to ſome Friends to judge whether I ought not to make him ſatisfaction for that Fine; I told him, if he was not ſatisfied he might, then he began to mention who to have to hear the cauſe and by whoſe judgment we might ſit down; I told him he might chuſe whom he pleaſed himſelf, ſo be they were Honeſt Faithful Friends, and had a good ſence of Truth, I would freely give up my cauſe to them for my part, and ſtand by their judgment. Then after ſome time he told me <hi>Giles Barnardiſton</hi> he knew was my very good Friend, and ſo he was his, and if he would he ſhould have the hearing of the cauſe, and if the ſaid <hi>G. B.</hi> did not judge his Demand to be reaſonable, he would deſiſt and proceed no further in it; ſo I was contented, and we appointed where to meet next Day about it, which accordingly we did; and when we came together, <hi>F. B.</hi> laid his cauſe before him, who when he had heard, he ſeemed much grieved at <hi>F. B.</hi> and told him he ſee no cauſe why <hi>S. C.</hi> ſhould pay his Demand, for it was unjuſt, &amp;c. But <hi>F. B.</hi> broke his promiſe made to me the day before, and would not ſtand by <hi>G. B</hi>'s judgment. Then he ſaid he would lay it before the Yearly Meeting, I told him if he did it would not make to his honour.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109781:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>He ſaid, he would propoſe a Queſtion about it, I told him if he did ſtate his Queſtion fairly as the thing was, I would be ſilent, and not only hear the Meetings judgment, but would ſit down by their judgment: But if his Queſtion or Words tended to that purpoſe as if I would not tell my Name, then I would give the Meeting account how the matter was, for I knew my ſelf clear, ſo when he came into the Meeting, he propoſed his Queſtion according to his own mind, but not according to the true ſtate of our cauſe about which he differed with me; then I told them plainly how the matter was, and the next day at <hi>Horſly-down,</hi> I offered to ſtand by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the meeting, and deſired <hi>F. B.</hi> to do the like, and that what the meetings judgment was we might both agree to it: this was the ſecond time I gave it up, but <hi>F. B.</hi> ſtood ſilent at the time, and would not ſay either that he would or would not, ſo the meeting could give no poſitive judgment in the caſe. Then ſome time after I was gone into the Low Countries, in which time he ſent a Letter to my Houſe, to meet him at our monthly meeting, ſo after I was come home, I met him at a monthly meeting at <hi>Chakes,</hi> the 4th of the 8th month, 1676. where he complained to the meeting that he had ſuffered a Fine of Fifteen Pound for me, and I refuſed to make him ſatisfaction, and he told the meeting that the cauſe he was fined was for my not telling my Name, ſo when the meeting had heard us both, they gave their judgment, and made a Record thereof in the Monthly Book, that I was not Guilty, in not declaring my Name, it not being of me demanded and told by another, which was himſelf, (viz) F. B. as I made it appear there, and which he did not deny) after which the meeting accounted he would have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109781:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>been at quiet: then at a Quarterly meeting at <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denham</hi> in the iſle of <hi>Eley;</hi> held in the 10th month 1676, F<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> B. complained to the quarterly meeting, then ſome in that meeting, ſaid that bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſineſs was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before by the monthly meeting, therefore it ought not to be ſpoken of at the quarterly meeting; then <hi>F.</hi> B. alledged that it was not ended, for he did not give it up to the meeting to end it, whereupon I asked him if he would give it up to this quarterly meeting to be ended by them, and would ſtand by the end they made? he ſaid he would, then the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard us both concerning the matter which we had to propound, and then deſired us to go out of the meeting untill they called for us, which we did, and when they were agreed we were called, and the meetings judgment was, they ſaw no cauſe of blame in me for that which <hi>F. B.</hi> accuſed me, neither could they award me to give him any mony. But deſired we ſhould be Lovers and Friends as we had formerly been, and if I had freedom in my ſelf to give him any thing I might, if not he ought to be content.</p>
            <p>Then after this the next Yearly Meeting follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he went to London again, and complained to <hi>W. Penn</hi> telling him he could not have a fair hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Friends in the Country, concerning the difference between him and me <hi>S. C.</hi> about the Fine, ſo <hi>William</hi> appointed him and I to come to <hi>Edward Man's,</hi> where <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> with other Friends would be, which accordingly we did, and there he was heard by <hi>G. F.</hi> and many other antient Friends, what he had to ſay and I alſo, where I again offered to give up my cauſe to <hi>G. F.</hi> or to all the Friends there or to any part of them in order to decide the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence depending between F. B. and my ſelf, and to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109781:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtand to their Judgment, and deſired him to do the like, that the buſineſs might be ended, he ſaid, no he would not give it up to them, but it ſhall be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at our own Quarterly Meeting, and he would put it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0 or 12 Friends that ſhould be choſen neither by him nor me, but by the meeting; and them he would commit his cauſe unto and would ſtand by their Judgment, then Friends deſired an Agreement ſhould be drawn up, and we ſhould ſet our Hands to it, and they would witneſs it, that ſo it might be performed, that there might be no more difference about this buſineſs, and one Friend began to write, then F. B ſaid, let me write the Order my ſelf, for I know my own mind beſt; ſo he took the Pen and Paper, and with his own Hand drew this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der following, and ſet his hand to it and ſo did I and Nine Friends were witneſſes to this our agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. (viz)</p>
            <p>MEmorandum, that upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that Friends in the Quarterly Meeting in the Iſle of <hi>Eley,</hi> do chuſe and elect 10 or 12 Friends to hear and determine the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie betwixt <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Cater,</hi> relating to the Fine which the ſaid <hi>F. B.</hi> was fined for the Speaker at a Meeting in <hi>Lakenheath;</hi> and all other Controverſies they the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109781:10"/>ſaid <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> and <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi> do hereby promiſe to ſtand to this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal determination under their Hands, and for the future to ceaſe from all Controverſie touching any matter now depending between them.</p>
            <p>Witneſs their Hands this 9th of the 4th mo. 1677.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sam. Cater.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſſes to it,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Giles Barnardiſton</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Burnyeat</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Whitehead</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ambroſe Rigge</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leonard Fell</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Whaley.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To the Friends at the Quarterly Meeting in the Iſle of <hi>Eley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Friends, <hi>We deſire you that when this buſineſs comes before you, that there may be a final end put unto it, that there may be no more trouble about it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>George Whitehead Stephen Criſp.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109781:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Then the aforeſaid Agreement was delivered into a Friends hand by both our conſents to keep, and for him to deliver it to the Quarterly meeting, and <hi>F. B.</hi> there himſelf took a Copy of it which he kept. Then at the Quarterly meeting the Order was produced, and Friends diſcourſed the matter about chuſing the men, and would have had us to chuſe them our ſelves, that is 6 Friends each of us; but I told them I was not free ſo to do, leſt <hi>F. B.</hi> ſhould not ſtand to what they did, if they went con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Agreement whereunto he had ſet his hand: So the meeting deſired us to go out, ſo we withdrew, and then they choſe the 12 Friends out of the meeting in manner following, viz. the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſe one Friend and agreed that he ſhould chuſe whom he pleaſed next, and ſo the laſt man choſen was to chuſe the next, until the 12 were all choſen; and when they had choſen the 12, they ſent for us into the meeting, and told us how <hi>they had choſen them;</hi> and read their Names unto us; then I told them, <hi>I was well ſatisfied with the Choiſe and what they did in the matter, wherein they were to be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between</hi> F. B. <hi>and my ſelf, I would be contented to ſtand-by their Judgments;</hi> and <hi>F. Bugg</hi> promiſed he would do the like, then they withdrew to a Friends houſe to draw up their Award; and F. B. asked me if I would not go and open my Cauſe to them, I told him, <hi>He might do what he pleaſed in the matter for himſelf, but I ſee no need for it, for it had been ſpoken of ſo often before them, that they could not be without a Knowledge of it;</hi> but he went to them and ſpake what he pleaſed, and ſo left them to give Judgment; ſo when they had agreed and drawn up their Award, they ſent for us, and read their Award to us; the ſubſtance thereof was.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109781:11"/>
            <p>THey found <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> clear of that Demand of <hi>Francis Buggs:</hi> Therefore Awarded that he was to Pay <hi>F. B.</hi> Nothing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that all Differences that have ariſen between them about that and all other things, be from this Day fully ended; and that they may be Lovers and Friends as they were before the Difference happened.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators Names.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Ainſloe, Wil. Brazier,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Webbe, Robert Smith,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Prine, Peter Watſon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rich. Read, Sam. Fulbugg,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phillip Taylor, Edward Firth,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jacob Baker, Edward Love.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now when they read this Award, F. B. ſaid they had given away his cauſe, but however he would be quiet and meddle no more: But he ſoon broke his promiſe again, and in a little time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he began to threaten the Arbitrators, and wrote to them to that purpoſe, that they had given away
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109781:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>his mony, and thereby had done him wrong, and although that by their Arbitration he had now done with <hi>S. C.</hi> But now he intended to begin with them, for there was a Law in the Nation, <hi>That if</hi> Arbitrators <hi>did not do that which is Equal and Juſt when ſo Choſen, the Party Grieved might recover Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of them;</hi> and they ſhould have no more favour then the Law would afford them: Then about this for a time he made a great adoe; and gave a Lawyer Brevitts,<note place="margin">☞</note> whereby he inſtructed him how to plead againſt Friends, and of the ſtate of his cauſe, to come to our Quarterly Meeting to plead his cauſe; which ſaid Breviats the Lawyer ſhewed to <hi>William Penn</hi> and <hi>Thomas Rudyard,</hi> after which the matter fell, and the Lawyer never came to our Meeting; then he began again with me, and ſent to me to have another Arbritation, and Quarrelled with me again for the Fifteen Pound: But I not having freedom to grant his deſire, nor to meddle with him any more ſo that he could not have his will of me: Then he Threatened to prefer <hi>A Bill in Chaucery</hi> againſt me for his Mony, and went to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Penn,</hi> and ſhewed him one that he had prepared, (as I was Informed) Then <hi>William Penn</hi> being grieved that the Enemies of Truth ſhould have ſuch cauſe given them to rejoyce over us, by having ſuch a cauſe as that brought before them; he with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Friend wrote to me, that if I could, to get an end of this Buſineſs it might be well, for although they believed that his Demands was very unjuſt, and there was nothing due to him upon that account, and that he was much to blame, yet for Peace ſake, if it could be made an end of it might be well, then I knowing he had deſired another Arbitration, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended to it, and ſent him word, that ſeeing he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109781:12"/>was yet diſquiet about this mony, if he knew how to have another Arbitration which would pleaſe him amongſt Friends, I would condiſcend to it, and put my Innocent cauſe once more upon Tryal, then he ſeemed to be pleaſed, and came over to my Houſe, and pretended all would be ended, for whether he had any money or not he would be tcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo he ſaid he would chuſe 6, and I ſhould chuſe 6 alſo, and withall he ſaid he would be bound with me to ſtand to the Award, which Bonds were made and ſealed: But when the Arbitrators came to meet, although they were neer to Agreement, yet they did not agree for after F. B. underſtood that they were like to agree, and his will not anſwered, he ſaid none ſhould give away his Mony for if it muſt be given away, he would give it away himſelf: And when the Arbitrators were come to an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and were drawing up the Award, then F. B. came in amongſt them, without being deſired, and called <hi>Edward Neal</hi> one of the ſaid Arbitrators, to ſpeak with him, and when he came in again from him, he would not ſtand to what he had Agreed to before, then they could go no further, for F. B. made the Bonds himſelf, &amp; they were made, ſo that if all the 12, or ſo many of them as there met were all to agree, or elſe their Award was not to ſtand good, whereby it appears although he was willing to be bound to ſtand to the Award, yet he had made ſuch proviſion, that if he had not his will &amp; end An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, he would have nothing done, for be having provided ſuch a Man as would do what he would have him or nothing, as it did plainly appear to all honeſt Friends that were there preſent: Which thing was as wicked of <hi>F. B's</hi> part and him that joyned with him in his deceitful practice, as it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109781:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>was before when he promiſed, and gave it under his hand to ſtand to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and abide by the Award of the other 12 Friends choſe by the Meeting, and after they had done it, he promiſed to be quiet, and meddle no more in the matter ſo awarded, and ſo foully and ungodly went from his Word, whereby all may ſee that reads this Narrative of his Words and Actions, whether he hath not proved himſelf a falſe deceitfull Man, both to God and Man, and whether he hath not wickedly wronged his own Conſcience, by Covenant-breaking, Lying and Deceit, from time to time, for the ſake of Money, whereby all may perceive, that have any ſenſe of truth and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, how unfit he is to take upon him to treat about the Principles of true Religion, and to plead for Liberty of Conſcience, againſt Impoſition, who hath thus wilfully abuſed and defiled his own Conſcience for <hi>unjuſt gain.</hi> Then after they could not end it, I was much grieved to ſee the trouble that Friends and I had had, and yet the Buſineſs remained, I then took <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> aſide, and told him, that although I was well ſatisfied in my Conſcience that I had never done him wrong, and that I did not owe him one penny, and that his Demand was unjuſt and unreaſonable, yet for Peace ſake, rather than this difference ſhould Remain, to trouble Friends, and diquiet our ſelves, I would give him of my own free will, five Pounds towards his loſs relating to the ſaid Fine, his anſwer was, that would not do, ſo we part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at that time, than I ſpake to his Friend and Abettor <hi>Edw. Neale</hi> aforeſaid, and told him he had not done that day like an honeſt Friend in his Place, nor like a man that feared God, whoſe work is to make Peace, and purſue it with all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109781:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>men, and he and others of them, that <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> had Choſen, had an opportunity thereby to have made Peace in this matter, that ſo long had been troubleſome to the Church of God, but he more eſpecially I underſtood had hindered that day, by refuſing to Joyne with the reſt that would have done it, which days work would certainly become his burthen at one time or other; his anſwer was, we might make an end of it between our ſelves, if I would, for he knew <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi>'s end was <hi>not for Money,</hi> but Juſtice in the caſe, I told him, I n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver did ſee other by <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that his end was wholly for Money, neither was there any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the caſe, that he ſhould have 15 Pound of me for nothing, and beſides his words was always to me, <hi>give him ſo much Money,</hi> and he would be quiet, and when we were together alone at that time he ſaid the ſame; But I have not freedom to anſwer his unreaſonable dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds therein, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf clear of any thing of guilt concerning the matter whereof he charged me, now this was the ſeventh time that I had given up the aforeſaid caſe to the Judgment of Friends, and four of the 7 times <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> excepted of, and Joyned with me, and promiſed, and became engaged, as is before mentioned, to ſtand to the Award or Judgment of the Friends, to whom we gave up our Cauſe, but went from his word every time. Now the next thing, wherein like a Deceitful man, who ſhews himſelf void of any fear of God, as hath and yet will appear by his following actions, for he Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed his Coſin <hi>Geo. Smith</hi> of <hi>Littleport,</hi> through his Deceitful craft, and got the ſaid 15 Pound of him, who is <hi>Fran. Bug</hi>'s own Mothers Siſters Son, a man that hath been Convinced about 13
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109781:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>or 14 years, and ever ſince he came amongſt us, hath walked uprightly according to his meaſure, and hath been of a blameleſs Converſation amongſt Men from his Youth, and lives in good credit and reputation, a relation whereof he hath given, which hereafter followeth under his own hand; Alſo how far he was concerned in this matter by my Wife, under her Hand, whom <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> calls my Wife her Agent, as ſent by her, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when <hi>Edw. Neale, Will. Rogers,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Criſp,</hi> and others, whom <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> accounts of his party, who hath of late Joyned and Combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Spirit of diſcord and oppoſition againſt the Godly and mutual care of faithful men and women in their diſtinct Meetings, in ſeveral things which concerns our publick Teſtimony before the World, amongſt whom the Lord hath gathered us to bear Teſtimony againſt thoſe looſe and unjuſt ways, that many, both Prieſts and People, lives in and Practices in that weighty matter of <hi>Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,</hi> with ſeveral other things, comes to read this relation of <hi>Fran. Bug</hi>'s words and actions, and will yet own him as a Brother amongſt them, and as an Agent to Abet their cauſe without repentance, and making ſatisfaction, both by word and deed, for the wrong he hath done, as aforeſaid, its no great matter what they profeſs, neither will it be much to the diſhonour of honeſt and faithful men and women, to be reproached by them, but yet this I do ſay, and ſo I ſhall conclude this Buſineſs, that if it pleaſe God to give <hi>Fran. Bug,</hi> and <hi>Will. Rogers,</hi> and the reſt of them, true and unfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for that wherein they have done amiſs, whereby they have ſtrengthened the hands of evil doers, and laid ſtumbling blocks in the way of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109781:14"/>the ſimple, by their Writing and Printing in this wilful and unjuſt manner, againſt the faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, whoſe care hath been to keep all clean and ſavoury amongſt the People of God, I ſay, I ſhall be truly glad thereof, who am a friend to all that truly Love and Fear God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who am in ſtrait Boreds for the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt in</hi> Ely <hi>Priſon his</hi> 9th Month, 1682.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Cater.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>Elizabeth Cater<hi>'s Teſtimony.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HEre followeth a Teſtimony under <hi>Eliz. Cater</hi>'s hand, how She came to encourage <hi>G. Smith</hi> to Treat with <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> about his differing with her Husband <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> aforeſaid, and how farr ſhe gave him order, which was thus. <hi>Geo. Smith</hi> coming to my houſe one day when my husband was not at home, and told him that I was very much grieved and, troubled at <hi>Fran. Bug</hi>'s continuing ſo bad and envious againſt my husband, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I was ſatisfied, that what he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109781:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo furiouſly abuſed him for, was unjuſt, upon which account my husband hath not freedom to anſwer his unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Demand, I could be glad it were ſome ways ended; then <hi>Geo. Smith</hi> told me that he alſo was much grieved for the difference, for ſaid he, I Love thy husband well, and <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> alſo, and he is my near Kinſman, for it doth trouble me that there ſhould be a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them, but I do account my Coſin is much out of the way in this matter, but if thou Pleaſe, I will ſpeak with him, and ſee if I can get him to be quiet, then I deſired him he would, and I told him withall, that although I knew that neither I nor my husband, owed <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> one penny, neither was there any due upon that account he Demanded, yet for Peace ſake, rather then my hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and friends ſhould be any longer diſquieted about it, I would part with ſome Money, if it cannot be done without, although my husband knows
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109781:15"/>nothing of it, then <hi>Geo. Smith</hi> told me, he would take an opportunity, and ſpeak with him, and he did not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but to make an end of the buſineſs with little Money, if any at all: This is the truth of the matter, to ſhew how farr I was Concern'd therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eliz. Cater.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>An Account given by <hi>George Smith,</hi> concerning the Mony which <hi>Fra. Bugg</hi> deceitfully obtained from him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Samuel Cater.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THeſe are to certify all into whoſe hands this may come, That whereas there was a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence long depending, made by <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> with <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> about a Fine which the ſaid <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> demanded of <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> which he had not Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to pay him, looking upon his demand therein to be unjuſt; and I coming to <hi>Sam. Caters</hi> houſe, as is by his Wife before mentioned, was willing out of true Love, which I had to them both, and for Peace ſake, to concern my ſelf about it, hoping to have made Peace betwixt them. A true Account of what paſs'd betwixt my Coſin <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> and my ſelf, is as followeth.</p>
            <p>There being a Fair at a Town where my Coſin <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> Lives, to which I had an occaſion to go; I took that opportunity to Speak with him about
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109781:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>that difference between him and <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> where I deſired it might be at an end, and he told <hi>Me,</hi> it might, if <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> pleaſed, for he counted he had Right to the Money he demanded of him, But I told him, I did believe he had no Right to it, neither by the Law of God nor Man: And beſides, I told him, I did find that Friends are in General diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied about thy demand in this matter, therefore I would be glad thou wouldeſt deſiſt, and be at quiet, and not to Trouble <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> nor his Friends any further about it: To which he ſaid, it is my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I have a Right to the Money I demand of him: then in ſhort I told him, I could be glad I could Perſwade him to deſiſt, and be at quiet in this Matter without any Money: But rather than the difference ſhould continue betwixt <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and Him, for Peace Sake, I would give him 5 Pounds, though I never have it of <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> for he knows nothing of my Treating with thee at this time, but that would not do, then I offered him 7 Pounds 10 Shillings, but he was not willing to take it: Then I deſired him to Conſider of it, and Proceed no further about <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> and he told me, he would meet me at <hi>Ely</hi> Fair about three Weeks hence, and if I and he could make an end of it, then we would. And when I was at <hi>Ely</hi> Fair ſelling of goods, he came to me, and asked if I had time to Treat about that I was ſpeaking to him at his houſe lately, I told him my occaſion was in ſelling of my goods, he told <hi>Me</hi> we ſhould ſoon have done about that concern: Then we went to an Inn to Treat about it, and I told him ſtill I would give 7 Pound 10 Shillings rather than the difference ſhould continue between <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and him, His Anſwer was, Coſin, I would have it all Tendered, for my Words Sake,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109781:16"/>but thou ſhalt ſee, my ends is not for Money, I told him, I had not ſo much Money, I had not above 5 Pound about me, Then he ſaid, I might Borrow 10 Pound for half an Hour, or thereabouts, which Time would ſerve for a Tender, then I told him, Coſin, I can Borrow ſo much of a Tradeſman in Town, to make thee a Tender, but if thou be minded to keep it all, I will not do it. Rather than I will give the whole 15 Pound, I will leave the Buſineſs as I found it: Then He ſaid, He would have it all tendered, but ſaid he, I will Promiſe thee I will not Pocket a Penny of it, Then I went and Borrowed 10 Pound and Tendered him the whole 15 Pound, and when he had it, he took it, and put it all into his Pocket, whereby he broke his promiſe made to me, before I tendered it, that he would not Pocket a Penny of it. Then after a little time I deſired to have the 10 Pounds that I Borrowed to carry the Man it again whom I Borrowed it of for Half an Hour to make a Tender with, and which <hi>Fran. Bug</hi> ſaid, it would be long enough to Borrow it for. Then he began to make Evaſions, and ſaid, he would have me let it alone till to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Morning, and he would Treat with <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> about it, with the Money in his Pocket. And then he pull'd out a Paper, and ſaid, if <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> would Signe that Paper, he ſhould have the Money again, then I told him that was not our concluſion, for, ſaid I, thou ſaidſt nothing of this Paper to me before I tendered the Money, and when I had ſeen it, I told him, I did believe that <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> would not ſet his Hand to it, neither do I ſee any Reaſon he ſhould, Then he told me, that to Morrow Morning, whether <hi>S. Cater</hi> would ſet his Hand to that Paper or not, he would Pay the 10 Pound
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109781:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>where I Borrowed it, or leave it with a Friend in <hi>Ely</hi> to Pay him; and the 5. Pound to a Brother of Mine, as he went home, to whom I owed the Money, which he did not do, but contrary to his Promiſe kept all the Money to this day. This is a true Relation of this matter before Mentioned.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Witneſs my Hand. <hi>Geo. Smith.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Then after this came to be Spoke of abroad, and Friends came to hearof it, Friends deſired us to be both at a Monthly Meeting, that they might know the certainty of it, how it was concerning the matter, ſo at a Monthly Meeting at <hi>Chatteris</hi> the 7. day of the 2d. Month 1680, Friends heard us both what we could ſay about this matter. And I gave them a true account of the Buſineſs, how he obtained this Money from <hi>Me,</hi> and the Meeting were ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that he got it Unjuſtly. And made a Record in the Book to this effect, that <hi>Geo. Smiths</hi> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity was betray'd, and he ought to have his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney again.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>Edward Firth's <hi>Teſtimony.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis is to ſatisfie all where this may come, that whereas <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> hath made uſe of my Name, in a matter between his Coſin <hi>George Smith</hi> and him, wherein he ſaith, that I was a Witneſs for him againſt <hi>George Smith,</hi> which thing is not ſo,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109781:17"/>but I am a Witneſs for <hi>G. Smith</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi> And he to make a Cover for himſelf, would make void my Evidence againſt him, and through his Deceit, would turn it from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Now the matter is this that I witneſſed at <hi>Chattris</hi> monthly Meeting that day that Friends had the hearing of them both, that I had ſpoken with the Man, that <hi>G. Smith</hi> had borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Mony of, to make a Tender with to <hi>Fran. Bugg,</hi> and asked him if he did remember <hi>G. Smith</hi>'s borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 10 Pound of him about ſuch a time, and he ſaid, <hi>Yes,</hi> and it was to make a tender of to ſome Body. Then it was asked him, if he could remember how long time he lent it him for; he ſaid, as near as he could remember, it was for about an hour. This was all that I was a Witneſs for at that Meeting, and whereby the Meeting was ſatisfied that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was borrowed. by <hi>G. Smith</hi> but to make a bare Tender with, and not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109781:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>that <hi>G. Smith</hi> intended that <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> ſhould keep the Mony. Now the advantage that <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> would take at this my evidence againſt <hi>G. Smith,</hi> is this, that <hi>G. Smith</hi> had ſaid, and doth yet ſay, he borrowed the Mony for half an hour, and the Man he ſaid, (as he Remembers) he lent it for about an hour; which neither diſproves <hi>G. Smith</hi> his Account, nor clears <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Witneſs my Hand</hi> Edward Firth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Coppy of a Letter ſent by <hi>G. Smith</hi> to <hi>Fran. Bugg.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Coſin Fran. Bugg.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſeen a large Paper of thine, which thou didſt ſend to Friends of the 2d days Meeting in <hi>London,</hi> in which thou haſt Revived the Old Buſineſs again, and therein haſt abuſed <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and my ſelf, by Miſrepreſenting the Buſineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter wherein I was concerned for <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> as formerly thou uſeſt to do. And thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109781:18"/>it is altogether contrary to the agreement which was made at the Quarterly Meeting in <hi>Hadenham</hi> the 10th Month 1680.</p>
            <p>By which agreement, thou wert to ceaſe from any further Controverſy concerning this matter. At which time thou ſeemingly madeſt ſome ſhew of Repentance, for what thou hadſt written and done againſt <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and my ſelf; as appeared by what thou ſaidſt there to Friends that day, which begat ſome hopes in ſome Friends, that thou wouldſt not onely be quiet from being any more contentious and troubleſome to Friends and us, as thou hadſt formerly been, for ſeveral years: But that alſo thou wouldſt have Reſtored all the Money again, which thou through thy Subtilty and wicked craft obtained of me, and which thou in meaſure there confeſt in the Meeting, Saying, that thou did'ſt believe that when I tendered thee the Money, I did expect thou wouldſt have given it me again. Whereby thou therein cleared my Innocency, and manifeſted thy own Guilt, and Treacherous dealing with me in the matter. But now inſtead of anſwering the expectation of the Meeting, by returning the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny again, and making ſatisfaction for the wrong thou haſt done, thou haſt further Tranſgreſſed, and added ſin to ſin with a Witneſs. For before thou flattered'ſt, and through thy diſſimulation wenteſt beyond me, and got the Mony thereby, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to my Freedom and expectation, as thou thy ſelf confeſſedeſt in the Meeting. And now through thy diſſimulation, haſt abuſed the Quarterly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for when they told thee than thou art to return the Mony again that thou hadſt ſo unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained from thy Coſin <hi>G. Smith;</hi> thou deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Meeting to leave that to thee, for they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109781:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>did not know what was in thy Heart. Which words of thine, with thy Diſſembling Confeſſion and carriage then, cauſed the Meeting to leave the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of the Mony to thee at that time; telling thee, that they would not have thee think that they would forgive thee the Mony, or that they thought it was not due from thee, but did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that thou oughteſt to pay it, otherwiſe it would become thy Burden if thou becameſt not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt: But inſtead of paying the Mony, and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfaction for the wrong thou haſt done, thou art of late ſending thy wicked and malicious Papers abroad, to City and Country, in which thou again abuſeſt <hi>Samuel Cater,</hi> that is the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer and <hi>Me,</hi> whom thou ſo unjuſtly betrayed in this manner, whereby thou endeavoured to take away our good Names and Reputations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men. Oh Coſin, Bluſh, and now let Shame cover thy Face, what? do ſo Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly by <hi>Me,</hi> as thou haſt done in this matter; and abuſed <hi>Me</hi> beſides! But I know my ſelf clear of thy Lies and Slanders, and ſo I ſhall make it appear to thy Shame, if thou haſt any tenderneſs left in thee. Thou revileſt and ſpeakeſt evil of <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>S. C.</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But I tell thee, that if I knew ſo much againſt them as I do of thee, I ſhould not only turn my Back upon them, but alſo declare againſt them, as I ſhall againſt thee, and Manifeſt thy deceit. But I have cauſe to believe better things of them all. And for <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> whom thou ſo much abuſeſt, I know his converſation hath been ſuch among us, as becomes a Man that fears God, that it is not thy Lies that can hurt him; for he hath a Witneſs in our Conſciences, for his Faithful Service, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109781:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>upright Converſation among us. And now ſeeing thou wilt be not quiet, but haſt ſet the old buſineſs on Foot again, between thee and <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and my ſelf, about which thou haſt given uncertain reports. Now for the preventing all miſtakes, that the Truth may be known, I have given a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the buſineſs, ſo far as I have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with thee in the matter, how unjuſtly thou obtained the Mony from <hi>Me,</hi> and as unjuſtly keepeſt it to this day. And of thy wickedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting and wreſting my words and true intention in my Letter which I ſent thee, ſoon after thou hadſt defrauded me of my Mony, which was in anſwer to a Letter, which thou ſenteſt <hi>Me,</hi> which was like thy words and actions, when thou gotteſt the Mony of <hi>Me,</hi> in which thou endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to excuſe thy ſelf, and cover thy deceit, and wouldſt have had <hi>Me</hi> excuſe thee to <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> and his Wife, and have made ſome deceitful cover for thee, and not have told them the plain Truth as it was, which thing I abhor to do. And I praiſe God, Truth teaches <hi>Me</hi> better things than to Lie, and make deceitful covers, either for my ſelf or thee; Though thou Wickedly and Falſly inſinuateſt in this thy Scandalous and abuſeful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as if I was neceſſitated to give forth ſuch a report, as was not true, to get my Mony again of <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> which thou hadſt deceitfully obtained from <hi>Me,</hi> which inſinuation and equivecation of thine is as wickedly unjuſt, as the Action and deceitful work was before, and altogether untrue; for I never had any trouble to obtain my Mony again of <hi>Sam. Cater,</hi> though I do confeſs, if He nor his Wife would not have given it <hi>Me,</hi> I muſt have loſt it, neither could I have laid that blame
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109781:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon them, that is juſt upon thee, who betrayed <hi>Me</hi> out of my Mony; for <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, when I went about it, and his Wife but little: And it was near Four weeks after thou hadſt got the Mony before I ſpoke one word of it to <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> or his Wife. For indeed, I was aſhamed to tell them, how I was betrayed by thee, but when I did tell them, it was with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret and trouble, that of one ſo near related to <hi>Me,</hi> and whom I had once looked upon to be before <hi>Me</hi> in the Truth, and had a great love for, both as a Friend and Kinſman, I muſt now tell ſo bad a Story, if I told the whole Truth, which I found my ſelf bound in Conſcience to do, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I had been a partaker with thee in thy wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deed. So when I had told them the whole Truth of the matter from the beginning, then <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> ſaid to <hi>Me,</hi> thou haſt fallen into the Hands of 2 deceitful Man, who by his ſubtilty hath betrayed thee. But now thou ſhalt ſee, there is a difference between one that makes profeſſion of the Truth, and lives out of it, and them that deſire with their whole Heart to obey it, and do things anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereto. For ſeeing thou out of tenderneſs and true love to <hi>Me</hi> and my Wife, and alſo to him, (though he has abuſed thy love) didſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thy ſelf thus in this matter, thinking to have peace, and thereby haſt loſt thy Mony, I will pay thee it all again. So all the whole 15 Pound he did willingly pay, with the 3 Shillings alſo, which thou tookeſt for uſe of the 10 Pound (which I borrowed but for half an hour,) and thou keepeſt it, and cauſed <hi>Me</hi> to give thee Bond for it for 3 Months, with 3 Shillings uſe for it, or elſe I could not have paid the Man his Mony again, which I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109781:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>borrowed to make a Tender of to thee, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed he ſhould have his own Mony again in half an hour. All which proceedings of thine, I have given a true account, and let the Reader judge, into whoſe Hands it may come, whether thou haſt, done like a Man that pretends ſo much to Chriſtian Liberty and Honeſty; or indeed like a Man that hath common Honeſty; or rather in this matter, art a ſhame to both. For which I can truly ſay, I am grieved to ſee and know, and could have been glad at my Heart, if thou hadſt never given me this cauſe thus to write of thee, neither do I believe I ſhould, what ever I had ſuffered by thee, were there not a true concern of Conſcience upon <hi>Me</hi> for the clearing of Truth, and the ſatiſfying of all that deſires the certain knowledge of this matter, that ſo the Innocent may not be blamed, and all miſtakes may be prevented. And now I do yet ſay, what canſt thou think of <hi>Me?</hi> I could be truly glad and I am ſure, my Heart would greatly rejoyce in it, if yet thou mayeſt come to true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of theſe things of which thou ſtandeſt guilty, and which the Enemy of thy Soul hath led thee into, without which thou canſt never hate true Peace with God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Which is all at preſent from thy grieved and Abuſed Kinſman.</hi> George Smith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109781:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Francis Bugg,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Having lately received a Paper of thine, ſent by thee to <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> and the reſt of the Second days Meeting in <hi>London,</hi> a Copy of the ſame thou ſays thou ſent to me, and I returned it to thee back without opening it, and I am glad I did ſo; for thereby all may ſee that comes to underſtand it, that this old Controverſie is on Foot again between, <hi>Geo. Smith,</hi> my ſelf, and thee, and alſo it will appear who is the cauſe thereof, and that it is not me nor <hi>Geo. Smith,</hi> but thy ſelfe, that haſt revived it again, contrary to thy promiſe and engagement made to the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Hadenham,</hi> the 10th Month 1680. Where thou made agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Meeting, that from that day all defferences betwixt thee and <hi>Me,</hi> and thy Coſin <hi>Geo. Smith,</hi> ſhould ceaſe, and all Papers by all parties relating to the ſaid difference, to be brought to <hi>Ely Priſon,</hi> the firſt of the 11th Month 1680. and there to be burnt, whereunto accordingly thou cameſt to <hi>Me,</hi> and brought a great bundle of writings, and further ſaid, that there was all that was in thy Hands ſo far as thou knew, that thou had'ſt written about that Controverſie, which thou there burnt, and withal promiſed, that if thou did'ſt find any more, thou would'ſt burn them, and that alſo where there was any in any friends Hands that thou kneweſt of, thou would'ſt write to them to do the ſame, and as to any thing of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie that had been between us, concerning the Fine and all other matters, ſhould be fully ended
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109781:21"/>and done withall, according to the agreement and thy promiſe to the Quarterly Meeting, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thou made before two witneſſes then and there. But now contrary to thy engagement made alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo many faithful Friends, without any Regard to thy word, like a man that neither Regards <hi>Truth nor Honeſty,</hi> thou haſt in the aforeſaid Paper abuſed us again, as formerly thou uſe to do, before the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe at that Meeting to be quiet, without any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation given thee either by <hi>G. Smith</hi> or my ſelf that I know of, although we have had cauſe enough given us by thee, Firſt in thy not anſwering the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Meeting, which did believe thou would'ſt have Paid the Money again, which thou obtained ſo unjuſtly from thy Coſin <hi>Geo. Smith,</hi> as ſeveral friends that came from the Meeting told me they did believe thou would, and that it was the ſence of the Meeting, that thou oughteſt to do it. And Secondly, when thou broughteſt forth thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Book in Print, ſo ſtuffed with Lies and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Suggeſtions and Reflections, againſt ſeveral Honeſt and Faithful Men, who truly fear God, and are Serviceable in their Places wherein God hath ſet them. And whom thou didſt account ſuch, before the Enemy of thy Soul filled thy Heart with envy againſt the People of God, but thy end will be according to thy work if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not; and alſo thou ſayes in thy aforeſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that I was Conſcious to my ſelf of Guilt, (as thou ſuppoſes,) and therefore I would not open thy Paper, but ſent it to thee without looking in it, which ſuppoſition of thine is as falſe as it is wicked, for I could not be Conſcious of Guilt, knowing not what was in it, neither had I ever done thee any wrong, but have ſuffered much wrong by thee,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109781:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>as I ſhall make appear before I have done with thee, ſeeing thou haſt broken thy promiſe again, made both in Publick and alſo to Private Perſons, of being quiet with us, and art become a common Enemy to the People of God, and a falſe Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer againſt them. And having deteſted thy folly in ſuppoſing <hi>Me</hi> Guilty of thou knoweſt not what, becauſe I did not beſtow looking into thy abuſive Letter. Now I ſhall tell thee the reaſon why I did not unſeal it to look into it, I being truly ſenſible of thy reſtleſs ſtate and Condition, and how far thou art fallen and degenerated from the pure Divine Principle of Love and Life, wherein my fellowſhip ſtands with the Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, I did not believe that there was any thing in it that would Miniſter any Comfort unto <hi>Me,</hi> but on the contrary, as it doth appear, now through thy reſtleſs attempts its come to my Hand, And I give thee to know that well knowing my own Innocency in matters whereof thou Suggeſt evil againſt <hi>Me,</hi> in which I have true Peace with the Lord, I ſhould have been ſilent in making any reply thereunto, until God that made thee ſtops thy Mouth, and makes thy folly Manifeſt to all Men, as he hath made it Manifeſt unto <hi>Me</hi> ſeveral years ſince, were it not for the ſake of them that deſire a certain knowledge of the Truth of theſe things, whereof there goes uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reports abroad, that ſo ſuch may know the plain Truth of the manner of thy dealings with <hi>Me</hi> in that matter, which thou ſo long haſt been quarrelling with <hi>Me</hi> about. A plain Narrative of the whole matter I do now intend to give forth, and leave it to the witneſs of God in all People to judge, who hath done, or who hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109781:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>the wrong, either thee or I in this matter. Thou alſo ſaidſt in thy Paper, thy Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> as my Wife's agent, made the reſtitution for the Fine.</p>
            <p>As to that thy Coſin <hi>G. Smith</hi> is able to give account what he did in that Caſe, and I believe will. But if it be as thou ſayes, what is the matter then that thou ſtill quarreleſt with <hi>Me</hi> about the ſame thing again, for when Reſtitution is made, Controverſie amongſt Honeſt Men uſe to be at an end. But <hi>Francis,</hi> its to be feared that the Reſtitution thou got by thy Coſin <hi>G. Smith</hi> thou didſt not come by it fairly, but like a Crafty deceitful Man, without regard to <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Honeſty,</hi> went beyond the Man, and Trap and him out of his Mony, as will be made appear, and now thou haſt thus unjuſtly got that 15 Pound from thy Coſin, thou art uneaſie with it for thy own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (although thou haſt taken this Liberty to do ſo wickedly) cannot be at eaſe with it, neither is it poſſible thou ſhouldeſt, thy proceedings have been ſo unjuſt and unrighteous, from the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thy medling with <hi>Me,</hi> unto this day. And the firſt ſtep thou ſet wrong in this matter, which thou ſo long haſt abuſed <hi>Me</hi> about, was when thou turned Informer againſt <hi>Me,</hi> and told the Officers and Informers my Name in the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which I might have done my ſelf, if thou hadſt nor been ſo forward to have told them, and thereby prevented them of asking <hi>Me,</hi> for it was ever my practice ſo to do, when I have been in the like danger of ſufferings.</p>
            <p>And it is well known to Friends where <hi>I</hi> have Travelled, and which is alſo well known to thee. And as that was wrong, ſo was every ſtep thou haſt ſet ſince, about getting Mony of <hi>Me</hi> for thy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109781:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>work, and now thou haſt got this Mony of mine as unjuſtly as ever any Informer did, that I ever heard of, except thy Brother <hi>Judas,</hi> who betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt Jeſus for Mony, who after He had got it, Torment and Trouble was his Portion, as his end Manifeſted, and I wiſh thou mayeſt repent of this thy ungodly work thou art in, before it be too late, for thou muſt never expect true Peace in this unrighteous work of Darkneſs, which thou haſt of late followed.</p>
            <p>And now thou art writing to <hi>Me</hi> again, to have another Arbitration, when <hi>G. S.</hi> nor I never wrote word to thee ſince the time thou ſpeakeſt of its being ended. But <hi>Fran.</hi> I had Arbitrations enough with thee about this matter, yea too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, except thou wouldeſt have been truer to thy promiſes and engagements then thou haſt been, as I ſha;ll make appear to thy ſhame in an Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the buſineſs. Neither ſhall I trouble Friends nor my ſelf any more with thee in that kind, and whereas thou ſayeſt in thy Paper, if another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitration I will not admit of, then thou wouldeſt have <hi>Me</hi> to Sign a Paper which thou haſt ſent, to which I anſwer, that I have learned better things of Chriſt ſince I believed in his Name, who ſaith, <hi>That not one Sparrow ſhall fall to the Ground with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Fathers Providence, and that the very Hairs of our Heads are Numbered.</hi> Then to joyn with thee, to make Laws and impoſitions to bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of my Brethren to ſerve thy will, who haſt Erred from the Faith, which ſtands in the Power of Gods, as it appears by this thy new invented Cannon, that thou haſt here Contrived, whereby it appears, that when thou goeſt to a Meeting where there's a Friend that Miniſters, thou dareſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109781:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>not truſt God, whether he will ſuffer the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his truth and People to lay a Fine upon thee for thy Teſtimony, or not, for thou wilt make a proviſion to ſave thy ſelf if thou can, by impoſing upon Miniſtring Friends, to tell their Names and Habitations to Informers, whether they be asked or not, and what is this but to lay a Yoak where God hath laid none, and to Limit his Servants and Meſſengers, on whom he lays a true neceſſity at ſuch times, to declare and ſpeak as he moves by his Power, and gives them utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance by his Holy Spirit, and not to ſpeak as Man Teacheth, but as the Holy Ghoſt Teacheth, on ſuch thou wouldeſt lay a Bond that they muſt leave ſpeaking (as being moved by the Lord) and ſpeak as <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> hath preſcribed, or elſe they muſt be Noted as Tranſgreſſors of <hi>Francis Bugg</hi>'s new rule, which He hath preſcribed without ſujection to, which nothing will ſatisfie thee as it appears by this thy unruly work againſt <hi>Me,</hi> for although thou pretends, that if the Friends in the Miniſtry do not tell their Names, yet if they will make ſatisfaction it ſhall ſerve. But it is not ſo, for thou ſays in thy Paper, that my Wife by <hi>G. S.</hi> hath made thee Reſtitution, what is the matter then that thou art ſo diſquiet with <hi>Me,</hi> was it not enough for <hi>Me</hi> to looſe 15 Pound and 3 Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings by thee, who never was Penny the better by thee in my life, but wronged by thee before that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both by Word and Deed, but ſtill I muſt be thy object to vent thy wicked Poyſon at. What will nothing do except Conformity to thy new Orders, which is of thy own inventing, and that Unſcriptural too, no where ſpoken of, neither in the <hi>Old</hi> nor yet <hi>New-Testament,</hi> nor practiced by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109781:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt nor his Apoſtles. This Order I do not find to be Apoſtolical.</p>
            <p>Now this new invented preſcription which thou haſt ſent to <hi>Me</hi> to ſubſcribe, I have here ſet down in thy own words as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MEmorandum,</hi> I <hi>S. Cater,</hi> do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Teſtifie, that it is my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all Friends in the Miniſtry where they are Strangers, ought to tell their Names and Habitations upon the apparent ſight of Informers coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Meeting, taking Friends Names in Writing or otherwiſe, in Order to convict the Meeting, that ſo we all may ſtand in the like ſuffering Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; or if any have not Freedom thus to do, that then they ought to make ſatisfaction to ſuch who ſuffers for them, through their Concealing their Names and Habitations. And that ſuch as refuſe to perform his or their Place in either of theſe two particulars, ought from thence forth to be Reputed blame-worthy, and Noted as ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Witneſs my Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109781:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now this is the Canon (or Order) that <hi>F. B.</hi> hath contrived, and which he tells <hi>Me,</hi> if I will Sign, I ſhall have all my Mony again which He doth unjuſtly detain from <hi>Me.</hi> Which invented Order of his, I do in truth ſay, that for Conſcience ſake I cannot nor dare not Subſcribe, although I for refuſing do looſe all my 15 Pound which He hath gotten into his Hand for theſe Reaſons follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is not my Judgment that all Friends in the Miniſtry are bound, without being asked, to tell Informers their Names and Habitations, being not thereunto required by the Lord, whoſe mind they then have, being Miniſtring in the power of Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe word they are to declare Faithfully, and not their own nor <hi>F. B</hi>'s. Secondly, it is my Judgment that all Friends that Miniſters in the Name and Power of the Lord, are to be left to do in that, as in their Faith and Freedom they ſhall ſee Meet, they will anſwer it to God, and are not to be Limited by <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> nor any other what to ſay, nor what anſwer to make, when <hi>Informers</hi> and Perſecuters come into a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where they are Miniſtring. Thirdly, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this new invented Order of <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi>'s tends to the exerciſing Rule and Lordſhip over the Faith and Conſciences of our Bretheren, and therefore I cannot ſet my Hand to it. Fourthly, I do account it a low and baſe thing of <hi>Fran. Bugg,</hi> to make ſuch a Law, and to proffer <hi>Me</hi> 15 Pound to make <hi>Me</hi> his Proſelite, or to be an Abettor of his evill Inventions, a thing altogether out of truth, and contrary to the Antient practice thereof, for Friends to make or to be made Proſelites for the love of Money, and I ſhould Sin if I ſhould condeſcend to his deſires therein, and therefore I deny to do it.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109781:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fifthly, I do know the 15 Pound that <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> pretends ſo freely to give <hi>Me,</hi> if I will ſigne his new Invented Order, he hath wrongfully, by defraud, got into his Hand of my Mony, for which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares this new Order, and Impoſes upon <hi>Me</hi> to Sign, to keep <hi>Me</hi> out of the Mony, as it appears if I did not Sign it; And if I did Signe it, to make a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful cover for this his unjuſt Practice, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Dealing with his Coſin <hi>Geo. Smith,</hi> which I have not freedom to do, although he keeps <hi>Me</hi> ſtill without my Mony.</p>
            <p>And now I Query of <hi>F. Bugg</hi> and his Abetters, if any he have, ſeeing he is againſt new Orders, and all Impoſitions as he pretends, which have no Footing in the Scriptures. Why I ſhould not have my 15. Pound and 3. Shillings again, ſeeing I cannot for Conſcience ſake Subſcribe this his new Invented Order, that he hath preſcribed for <hi>Me</hi> to Signe, and which I do ſay (as before) I have not freedom to do, for the aforementioned reaſons. And whether <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> does not appear a Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter of tender Conſciences, contrary to what He pretends, if he keeps my Mony, becauſe I have not freedom to Subſcribe to this his new Rule.</p>
            <p>And thou ſaieſt if this be not a condeſcention ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, that is, either to Sign this Order of thine, or a new Arbitration, thou then askeſt <hi>Me</hi> what will Pleaſe <hi>Me,</hi> but that which will be well Pleaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, that is, for thee to Truly Repent of thy Lies and Deceitful Dealings, and acknowledg thy infaithfulneſs both to God and Man, and make Satisfaction for the wrong thou haſt done. This is that which I expect, and thou muſt do it before thou can'ſt come to have Peace with God, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109781:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>true Unity with his People; run whether thou wilt, and climbe as High as thou can'ſt, the Hand of the Lord will find thee out, and His Power will bring thee down, as he did the Angels of Old who kept not their firſt Eſtate, but loſt their own Habitations, which the Lord hath reſerved in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Chains of darkneſs, unto the Judgment of the great day, ſuch the Apoſtle calls raging Waves of the Sea, Foaming out their own ſhame, wandering Starrs unto whom is reſerved blackneſs and darkneſs for ever. Now <hi>Fran.</hi> notwithſtanding all thy Malice that thou haſt shewn againſt <hi>Me,</hi> and wrong thou haſt done <hi>Me,</hi> both by word and deed, I could be glad I could perceive that there were ſo much regard by thee to the Light of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that thou mighteſt come thereby to ſee how near thou dwells to theſe fallen Angels, and how much thy ſtate and condition now reſembles theirs, for thou haſt left thy Peaceable Habitation in the truth which the People of God injoys, and thy Life is now in ſtrife and contention, as appears by the Fruit thou brings forth. Thou art gone from the Love that thinks no evil, into hatred and ſtrife, in which thou makeſt and inventeſt all the evil thou canſt againſt the Servants of the Lord, as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the Fruits thou haſt brought forth. How haſt thou been Inventing Lies and Slanders, not only againſt <hi>Me,</hi> but many more of the Servants of the Lord, whereby thou Foameſt out thy Shame, for its a Shame for a man to tell Lies and break Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes from time to time, as thou haſt done, both before God and honeſt Men. And he that lives in the feare of God dare not do it, but they who departs from the true fear and awe of God, what will they not dare to do, as appears by this wicked Work of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109781:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>thine, and alſo by thy Book, by which thy ſcoffing Rude Spirit is Manifeſt, and thy hard Heartedneſs againſt the People of God, whom now in thy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy thou Endeavours to render them to be like the worſt of Men, even ſuch as formerly thou account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good Men, and truly ſerviceable in the Church of Chriſt, who are he ſame ſtill. But Envy hath blinded thy Eye, ſo that thou canſt not ſee them in their Places, becauſe thou haſt loſt the knowledg of thy own place, which thou ſhoulded have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in, even in low humility before the Lord, to have ſtill waited upon him for his Wiſdom to have Guided thee, and to have felt his Power through the daily Croſs, to Crucifie that Earthly wiſe comprehending part, in which thou compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the Truth in thy Head, but never came to enjoy the life of Truth in thy Heart and Soul, through the Death to thy own will, in which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly will thou ſpeaks and Acts like an evil unruly Beaſt, whoſe Mouth God will ſtop in his own time, to thy ſorrow without unfeigned Repentance.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Francis</hi> thou tells <hi>Me</hi> of giving <hi>Me</hi> 15 Pound to Sign this Paper of thine, but where is the Liberty of Conſcience thou Treats ſo much of in thy Book, Dedicated to <hi>Hen. North.</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>Wherein thou pretendeſt that all ought to be left free to the Liberty of their Conſcience, and not to be compel'd to any thing that they have not Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in themſelves to do. But in this Paper thou art far otherwiſe minded, for thou ſpeakeſt nothing of leaving <hi>Me</hi> to my Freedom in that matter of the 15 Pound. But I muſt either, contrary to my Freedom, ſet my Hand to that Paper that thou haſt contrived, or elſe condeſcend to have another Arbitration about it, which I cannot do
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109781:26"/> for the Reaſons aforeſaid, otherwiſe I muſt una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably loſe my Mony, which is far from leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Me</hi> to my Freedom, which in the aforeſaid Book, thou pretendeſt all ought to be left unto. But <hi>Francis,</hi> tell us, when thou makeſt anſwer, was the Dedicating of thy Book accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Ancient principles which thou pretends to own, or did Friends in the beginning Dedicate their Books in that manner, or is it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the making of a Man that hath loſt his Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the power of Truth, and now is creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Flattering with Men of the World, and admiting Mens perſons becauſe of advantage, as is ſpoken of in <hi>Jude,</hi> of them that fell from their firſt Habitation, and which thou haſt given juſt cauſe to believe thou haſt done. For although thou never wert ſo much in Truth as thou would have People believe, by thy aſſuming to take upon thee to Treat about the Principles of Truth, as received by us in the beginning, whith thou never experimentally wert a witneſs of, yet thou haſt known more of Truth then thou haſt obeyed or lived in. And thou complaineſt to <hi>H. N.</hi> of the miſchief of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> what Redreſs thou expected by complaining to him, is beſt known to thy ſelf, but what plainer impoſition could ever be invented by a Man, then this new Order of thine is, which thou hath ſent to <hi>Me,</hi> to have <hi>Me</hi> ſet my Hand to, and with as much ſeverity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeſt it upon <hi>Me,</hi> as thy Capacity will afford thee to do. Whereby it doth and will appear to <hi>H. N.</hi> Knight and others, when they come to ſee what thou haſt done, both before and alſo ſince thou wrote thy Book, that thou haſt diſſembled with them, and endeavoured to delude the World,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109781:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>to make them believe thou art againſt impoſing new Orders, and Preſcriptions upon tender Conſciences, when its no ſuch matter, as appears by thy Practice. But a Liberty to thy ſelf to Lie and Diſſemble, and abuſe Honeſt Men, as is plainly Manifeſted, both by thy Book and thy aforeſaid new preſcription, and thou art got to thy old accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Work of thine, in abuſing <hi>Me</hi> with Suggeſting; that ſince I was a Preacher and a Sufferer, through receiving Gifts and Rewards, I am become Rich, but I never was counted a Rich Man by thee, until thou turned Informer againſt <hi>Me,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded 15 Pounds of <hi>Me</hi> unjuſtly for thy work.</p>
            <p>And I not having Freedom to ſatisfie thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt demand, and Friends blameing thee for deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, thou then began to change thy Tale con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Me,</hi> that whereas thou uſed to ſpeak of to whom thou pleaſed of my outward Condition, below what it was, ſo now ever ſince, haſt ſpoke of it at a large Rate, and what end canſt thou have in it, but to be get a belief in People that <hi>S. C.</hi> is a Rich Man, that thereby thy Offence may ſeem the leſs, in that thou haſt gotten 15 <hi>l.</hi> 3 <hi>s.</hi> of mine, for that which neither the Law of God nor Man allows thee one penny. But <hi>Fran.</hi> what I have as to the outward, I came Honeſtly by, and I wiſh that thou hadeſt no more in thy poſſeſſion then thou cameſt as truly and as juſtly by as I have come by what I have, and then it would be better for <hi>Me</hi> and mine by near 20 Pounds. And as to what I have, is beſt known to my ſelf, and I never complained to thee nor any other of want, neither have thee or others ever heard <hi>Me</hi> Boaſt of what I had in this World, but am well contented with ſuch things as I have, I praiſe the Lord for it, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109781:27"/>If than couldeſt have been ſo, thou wouldeſt never have troubled <hi>Me</hi> and others ſo much as thou haſt done, for that which is none of thy own. And again, <hi>Fran.</hi> thou Suggeſts in the aforeſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Paper of thine, as if ſince I was a Preacher, and a sufferer, I am become Rich thereby, to that I anſwer, I have been a Preacher of Truth, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Meaſure, and a ſufferer for the ſame, before thou kneweſt any thing of the Truth or <hi>Me</hi> either, in all which time its well known to God and to faithful Friends, both at Home and Abroad, my Converſation hath been without coveting any thing that was other Mens, but have from time to time taken an Honeſt care for <hi>Me</hi> and mine, that we might not be Burdenſome to any (its known to the Lord) and all Honeſt Friends, who hath known my Converſation longer then thou haſt done, who can witneſs to the Truth of what I ſay in this matter, and therefore what ſuch rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Rabſhecahs</hi> as thou ſayeſt is little to <hi>Me,</hi> who haſt forſaken the Truth, and art turned aſide to Lies. And now in anſwer to thy unjuſt charge and Slander in this kind, I do ſay, that I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver inriched as to the things of this World, either by Preaching or Suffering in that manner as is by thee Suggeſted, and I do ſay thy charge is falſe and Scandalous, and proceeds from a Lying Spirits, clear thy ſelf as well as thou canſt, and if thou thinkeſt thou canſt prove the contrary by Honeſter Men then thy ſelf, thou mayeſt go about it.</p>
            <p>I ask no Favour at thy Hand, as thou knoweſt I have told thee before now, for I have Truth and the witneſs of a good Conſcience on my ſide in theſe things whereof thou falſly accuſes <hi>Me,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have true Peace. And now whereas thou askes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109781:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>if thou hadſt no colour of right to the Mony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, (which thou defrauded thy Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> in the Gaining of.) Anſwer, that will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the Narrative, whether thou hadeſt or not, to all that deſire to know the certainty of that buſineſs, when they come to know the Truth as it is, and then I ſhall leave it to the witneſs of God in all their Conſciences, to judge who hath done and acted like a Chriſtian <hi>Quaker,</hi> or like an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, whether thee or I in this matter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou haſt been ſo long troubleſome to <hi>Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which is all at preſent, but to let thee know, that I have given a full and true Narrative from the beginning,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From him who is a Sufferer by thee, as I am under the Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prieſts for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, in which I have true Peace.</hi> Samuel Cater.</signed>
               <dateline>Ely Priſon <date>the 3d. of the 8th Month 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:109781:28"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRan. Bugg,</hi> thou haſt falſly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, as if thy Coſin <hi>G. Smith</hi> had hard work to get his Mony again of <hi>Me,</hi> notwithſtanding (adds thou) thy Wife ſent him, as thou told <hi>Me</hi> thy ſelf: Which inſinuation of thine is falſe, and thy Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> will prove it ſo, and for thee to ſay, I told thee my Wife ſent him, is a lie of thy own making, which thou haſt put in to make out thy matter as thou wouldeſt have it, an evil thou art too much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed unto, for I never told thee ſo, but do well remember ſtill what I ſaid, which was, that I know nothing of <hi>G. S</hi>'s. treating with thee, but my Wife did, as I underſtood after thou hadeſt got the Mony, as will appear in the Narrative, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>S. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109781:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>S. Caters <hi>Letter to</hi> F. Bugg.</head>
            <p>Thine I have received Dated the 8th of the 10th Month, 1682. Wherein thou ſayeſt thou didſt not ſend thy other Letter before this for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, not to revive the old one: But <hi>Fran.</hi> that is falſe, and thy Letter and the uſe thou makes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of proves the contrary to any that have ſeen or may ſee the ſame, for thou haſt not therein written to <hi>Me</hi> and thy Coſin <hi>Geo. Smith</hi> in order to make us ſatisfaction for the wrong thou haſt formerly done us, but thou haſt again therein abuſed us, and wrote Lies to exuſe thy ſelf about the old concern; which is not a way to ſtop controverſie, but to increaſe it, and further, if thou hadeſt been minded that it ſhould not have been revived again, why dideſt thou ſend thy mallicious Letter to <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> and to the 2d days Meeting in <hi>London,</hi> who ſee and are ſatified it was to revive the controverſie again; and again, why dideſt thou ſend the ſame Letter or a Copy of it to <hi>Ann Dockwra,</hi> letting her know thou hadeſt ſent that Letter to <hi>Me,</hi> and that I had ſent it back to thee again without opening of it, and She ſays that thou wert minded to make it Publick, only She accompted She had perſwaded thee to the contrary by ſomething Shee had wrote to thee, and withall Shee ſaid, that I had done well in that I did not look into thy Letter, and thereby have been ſtirred up to enter into further controverſie again with thee, ſo that She as well as others that have come to the ſight of thy Letter, do ſee that the tendency thereof was, and is for controverſie: but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109781:29"/>thou ſayeſt thou Intends to Manifeſt <hi>Me</hi> to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viver of the Old contreverſy, becauſe thou believes I have ſpoke of it; and that thou mayeſt have wherewith to accuſe <hi>Me,</hi> thou like one of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in th <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> (when in force) Queries of <hi>Me</hi> in thy Letter, whether at one time or other I have not ſpoke of it, ſince the agreement was made between the Quarterly Meeting and thee? for ſayeſt thou, if <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> have ſpoke of it, then the agreement of the Quarterly Meeting is broak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, yet alſo ſayeſt, thou knoweſt not that ever thou Covenanted or promiſed not to write a Letter to <hi>Me</hi> about it: to that I anſwer, if thou that wert at the Quarterly Meeting, and there made an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the Meeting, and promiſed to ceaſe from all Controverſie, and that all the writings thou hadſt writ about the Old Controverſie in general, ſhould be by thee brought to <hi>Ely</hi> Priſon in the 11th Month following, and there be burnt, which thou ſaidſt thou didſt, even all that were in thy Hand, and what was in thy other Friends Hands, thou ſaidſt thou wouldeſt ſend to them to do the like. Now (ſay I,) if thou wert at the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting and made the promiſe and agreement with them thy ſelf, doeſt not look upon they ſelf at bound by that Order or agreement, from writing to <hi>Me</hi> and others about the ſame Controverſie again, how comes it to paſs, that I, who was not at the Meeting, could be bound by that Order and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not to ſpeak of it.</p>
            <p>For of <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> hath ſpoken of it, ſayeſt thou, the Order of the Quarterly Meeting is broaken on his part, but I never ſaw any ſuch agreement, this is ſtrange Logick, yea, Confuſion indeed, its like the reſt of thy proceedings about and concerning
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109781:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>this matter and thou wilt have as hard work to prove this, as thou haſt to prove that I refuſed to tell my Name in <hi>Laken-Heath</hi> Meeting, which is falſe, and may be proved ſo. Thou alſo ſpeaks as if the report of this Controverſie was in <hi>London, Bristol, Hartford, Lincoln, &amp;c.</hi> whereby thou wert abuſed and miſpreſented: what then, if it were ſo that this buſineſs follows thee, and thy malicious Book, if thou haſt done well in it, thou needs not be aſhamed of it, but if thou haſt done evil, why doeſt thou not make ſatisfaction, ſeeing thou pretends ſo much to be a Chriſtian <hi>Quaker:</hi> But <hi>Francis,</hi> I am apt to believe, that not any have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed thee therein, for who can ſpeak worſe of thee then thou deſerves? And beſides, if it be ſpoken of in thoſe places aforeſaid, muſt it needs follow, that it was through my ſpeaking of it? was it not publick to the Nation? does not many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds know how unjuſtly thou demanded that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Me,</hi> and how reſtleſs thou wert to obtain it, &amp; when thou hadſt got it in that deceitful manner of thy Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> did not he give accompt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Monthly Meeting? and were not Friends ſatisfied that thou went beyond him, and gave it as their judgment, that his ſimplicity was betrayed, and that he ought to have his Mony again? and did not he give the ſame accompt again to the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Meeting, before Friends of five ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and could this be a private buſineſs to be kept from being ſpoken of by <hi>Me?</hi> but I ſuppoſe thou thinks, I may have ſpoke of it to ſome body or other that might ask <hi>Me,</hi> if <hi>F. B.</hi> had paid <hi>Me,</hi> or <hi>G. S.</hi> the 15 <hi>l.</hi> 3 Shillings he got ſo unjuſtly into his Hands, which the Meeting expected he would have returned again, as well as burn his writings? As
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109781:30"/>to that let <hi>Me</hi> know when thou writes again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what thou wouldeſt have me to ſay about it; when I am asked, ſince I have not Freedom to tell a Lie to cover thy deceit, and whereas thou offers in thine, to return <hi>Me</hi> 7 Pounds to Shillings, if I will accept it as Token of thy condeſcention, which thou ſayeſt, thou haſt told ſome Friends of, and that thou wouldeſt give <hi>Me</hi> ſo much Mony as a Free Gift; To that I anſwer, I have neither need nor Freedome to receive ſuch Gifts of thee: But that which I do expect and deſire of thee, is to return to <hi>Me</hi> or thy Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> that 15 Pounds 3 Shilling, which thou ſo unjuſtly obtained from, him and whereunto I have juſt right, and thou mayeſt keep thy Gifts for them that will accept of them form I deſire nothing of thee but my own, neither ſhall I receive it, but as my own: and as to thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <hi>Me</hi> to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who lay Heavy Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens upon the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> its but one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Slanders, and hard and ungodly Speeches, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou muſt give an account to the Lord for; ſo its known to the Lord and to Faithful Friends my Innocency both in that and other things whereof thou haſt unjuſtly accuſed <hi>Me</hi> and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friends, who truly fears God, and are clear and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in the ſight of God, of thoſe things tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chargeſt them with, for which thou haſt a bitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Cup to Drink at the Lords Hand, who will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> acquit the workers of iniquity, who ſin againſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> light in their own Conſciences, as thou haſt do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for ſeveral years.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll at preſent, from him who deſires Repentance before Mercy be hid from thy Eyes.</hi> Samuel Cate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Ely Priſon <date>the 25th of the 10th Month, 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:109781:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Sam. Cater</hi>'s Letter to <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> the 26th of the 10th Month, 1682.</head>
            <p>THis is to let thee know, that if thou wilt not make thy Coſin <hi>G. Smith</hi> and my ſelf ſatisfaction for the wrong thou haſt done us, both by word and deed, and alſo call in thy wicked Book, which thou haſt cauſed to be Printed, in which thou haſt belied, abuſed, and miſrepreſented Friends to the World, then we ſhall make thy ungodly Accounts, and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent proceedings more Manifeſt then ever we thought to have done, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have a Narrative ready for the Preſs, but if thou wilt call in thy Book, an as Publickly own thy Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as thou haſt given the offence, and thereby clear Friends of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thou haſt caſt upon them, then we ſhall ſtop any further proceedings
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109781:31"/>againſt thee in this matter: To this I deſire thy ſpeedy anſwer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From him who hath long been much wronged and Abuſed by thee.</hi> Samuel Cater.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>F. B.</hi> this <hi>Sam. Cater</hi> deſired ſhould be given thee, deſiring thy preſent anſwer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Samuel Cater,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis day I received thine, Dated the 26th of the 10th Month, and am not ſenſible, <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Not ſensible.</hi> No, for deceitfulneſs of Sin, Lying and Falſhood, do produce Hardneſs, and Blindneſs.</note> that I have wronged thee or my Coſin <hi>G. S.</hi> neither haſt thou therein ſaid, wherein I have, ſo that in anſwer, I dare ſay, if either of you,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109781:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>can make it appear, wherein I have wronged either of you, I will readily make you, or either of you ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if thou mean the Mony that my Coſin <hi>G. Smith</hi> paid me, as thy Wifes Meſſenger, <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>G. S.</hi> had no Meſſage from her, to pay the 15 Pounds.</note> or Ambaſſador, in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for the Fine I ſuffered for thee, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1675. And art not willing to ſtand by the Agreement made at Quarterly Meeting in <hi>Hadenham,</hi> the firſt of the 10th Month 1680. and then Recorded in their Quarterly Book, that <hi>All Controverſie betwixt thee, G. S. &amp; my ſelf ſhould ceaſe.</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">That was probably in hopes of thy amendment and making ſatisfaction for the wrong done, but inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hast not thou begun and renewed the Controverſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain against <hi>Sam. Cater.</hi>
               </note> I ſay, if thou art not willing to ſtand to the ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, but find thy ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie under it, I will, as I wrote thee word in my Letter, dated the 10th of the 6th Month 1682. very willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109781:32"/>conſent and agree, that thou ſhalt have a hearing <hi>De Novo</hi> by Perſons indifferently <note n="(d)" place="margin">How oft haſt thou ſhuffled with Arbitrators, and evaded their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and determinations in the caſe will ſuch Flams and Pretences as theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe thee.</note> Choſen by us both, <hi>viz.</hi> each others, 4, 6, 10, or 12 Perſons, and be bound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to ſtand to their award, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as for the calling in my Book; this I am willing to let the know: <hi>That on condition, the Orders</hi> upon Record in out 7th Book, which ſay, that for the time to come, no Marriages are to be either ſuffered or permitted, (meaning amongſt us) except the Parties, both Man and Woman, Publiſh their intentions twice before Mens Meeting, and twice <note n="(e)" place="margin">That was, that both might be concerned in a Godly care to ſee things clear and to prevent diſorder and Scandal what in them is.</note> before the Womens Meeting, they being (thou knoweſt) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and apart each from others, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109781:32"/>the Record a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>J.A.</hi> 
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Which was becauſe of his Irregular proceeding in Publiſhing his intention in the Womans abſence, to the Mens Meeting, and that but once, and refuſing to bring her to the next Meeting, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by Friends for example and ſatisfaction, as Friends had not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with his Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, it ſeems he had not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with them, Firſt, in that Orderly Method of both Perſons Publiſhing their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions twice before the time of Marriage.</note> for not taking Wife accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Friends; <hi>be raced out,</hi> and made void, that ſo thoſe that have Freedome <hi>to publiſh accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Orders</hi> 
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Why ſhould they then be Raced out, if a Freedom be granted to proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, what evil or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is in them ſimply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as Reaſon to Race them out, or wouldeſt thou not have thoſe Records Raced out that thou mayeſt make new ones, and Rule in thy looſe conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirit?</note> 
               <hi>may,</hi> and thoſe that are otherwiſe minded, may be left to their Freedom, and alſo the Book Intituled, <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt <hi>William Rogers, be called in,</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">No Reaſon nor Juſtice in that propoſition, we allow no ſuch bargain. Thoſe Books againſt <hi>Wil. Rogers,</hi> were occaſioned by his, which was firſt; and ought to be called in, therefore thou art an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Judge and Partial.</note> I ſay, on condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109781:33"/>that theſe things may be done, I am willing to call in mine, and ſhall be willing to uſe any Chriſtian means for a thorough <hi>Reconciliation</hi> and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Breaches, <note n="(i)" place="margin">How canſt thou be any fit Inſtrument for ſuch a Chriſtian-work, who art in a Spirit of diſcord and Enmity thy ſelf?</note> But whereas thou ſeems to threaten me with a further Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a Narrative, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It doth not frighten me, neither do I think it would have been thus long detained from publiſhing in Charity or good will to me, hadſt not thee <hi>been Conſcious</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">If <hi>S. C.</hi> were ſo Conſcious, by the ſame reaſon he would not puliſh a Narrative at all, therefore his Publication of a Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative proves thee Guilty of preſumptuous and falſe Judgment in this matter.</note> to thy ſelf, that Publication thereof would have been a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means to have unmasked thee and ſuch as thee art: This is my ſence, and as ſpeedy an anſwer as I can well give thee who am thy well-wiſhing (though much abuſed) Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis Bugg.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:109781:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Joſhua Bangs <hi>Letter to</hi> F. B.</head>
            <p>I Sent <hi>F. B.</hi> a few Lines, to let him know, that if he had any thing to offer in his own defence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I gave him time to do it, whereupon he returned me a great Letter, to which I have given ſomething in anſwer, which is as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>F. B.</hi> thy great Letter Received, which is in Vindication of thy receiving the 5 <hi>l.</hi> of Juſtice <hi>Shelly</hi> which the <hi>Widow Root</hi> ſaid, was part of the 15 <hi>l.</hi> thou wert Fined for <hi>S. Cater;</hi> and withal could not believe that thou hadſt taken 15 <hi>l.</hi> of <hi>G.S.</hi> and that is it <hi>Edw. Swanton</hi> ſays, that Juſtices <hi>Shelly</hi> told him, that 5 <hi>l.</hi> of the 15 <hi>l.</hi> was returned again to thee, foraſmuch as but 10 <hi>l.</hi> could be Levied upon one Perſon for the offence of any other Perſon, according to the words of the Statute: But in thy introduction thou endeavoureſt to Invalidate what he can ſay about it, by ſaying, he was an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former,</hi> yes, he was an <hi>Informer,</hi> and had 40 <hi>s.</hi> for ſo doing, but did not Pocket one penny of it, but if being an <hi>Informer</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, or violating Obligations, excludes a Man being believed in any cauſed, who
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109781:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall believed <hi>F. B.</hi> in his own cauſe, for was not <hi>F. B.</hi> an <hi>Informer</hi> againſt <hi>S. C.</hi> in that <hi>Laken-Heath</hi> Meeting? And hath he not got 5 <hi>l.</hi> more then what he could be juſtly Fined for <hi>S. C.</hi> according to the Statute, for the Act ſays, (ſpeaking of one Perſon, being Fined for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Offence,) that it ſhall be at the diſcretion of the ſaid Juſtice, Juſtices or chief magiſtrate reſpectively, ſo as the ſame to be Levied on any one Perſon, in caſe of the Poverty of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offenders amount not in the <hi>whole</hi> to above the Sum of 10 <hi>l.</hi> And again, provided always, and be it enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no Perſon ſhall by any clauſe of this Act, be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pay above 10 <hi>l.</hi> for any one Meeting in regard of the Poverty of any Perſon or Perſons. What can be Plainer then this, but in Contradiction hereunto, ſays <hi>F.B.</hi> Juſtice <hi>Shelly</hi> and his other Counſellors told him, that for neglect of the Speaker, a Preachers declaring his Name and Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, one Perſon may be Fined 15 or 20 <hi>l.</hi> for his offence, or to this Effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Shelly</hi> was a Man I had no acquaintance with, but I have heard he was a Judicious underſtanding Man,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109781:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>and I much queſtion whether he ſpoke to that purpoſe, but rather take it to be of thy own Hatching, yet ſince Juſtice <hi>Shelly</hi> is Dead, if thy other Counſellor be alive, let him give his Reaſons under his Hand; with his Name to it, that we may know where to find him; for the time is coming thou wilt ſtand in need of the Aſſiſtance of ſuch a Counſellor, that can make lies ſeem true, bring ſomething out of nothing, and make a foul falſe Cauſe look fairly. And what I have ſaid, is not to Vindicate or commend <hi>Edw. Swanton</hi> wherein he hath done amiſs; not yet condemn <hi>F. B.</hi> for well-doing, neither do I know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there will be any neceſſity to make uſe of his Certificate, in Order to Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thy deceit, ſince thou haſt confeſſed ſo much, but if there be, becauſe the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Backs what he Certifies, the Juſtice ſaid, it will be as credible as any thing, thee and thy Counſellor can ſay, which ſo plainly Contradicts the Statute. And now, ſince thou haſt done as thou haſt, how canſt thou Eſcape the juſt imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Folly, or Knavery? Thou mentions much charge and coſt thou haſt been at in Journeys and otherwiſe, whoſe fault was that? Oh! but thou haſt a ſmooth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109781:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>turn for that too, becauſe thou couldeſt not have Arbitrators indifferently choſen, or to that effect: I Query, were they not ſuch as thou accepted of? And didſt thou not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to ſtand to their Award? Nay further, dideſt thou not ſay, after thou knew their Award, that thou wouldeſt ſit down by it, or ſtir no further in it, or to that purpoſe. But to return, notwithſtanding all thou canſt ſay for thy ſelf, I take notice what the <hi>Widow Root</hi> ſaid of thee, and how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident ſhe was of thy Honeſty, that thou wouldeſt not take 15 <hi>l.</hi> having 5 <hi>l.</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee again, ſee how ſome honeſt Friends are betraied into a conceitedneſs of thy Honeſty; ſo ſmooth and ſubtle have thy carriage been. I have alſo perſſed the Act, to find what colourable pretence thy Counſellor can have to ſay, that 15 <hi>l.</hi> or 20 <hi>l.</hi> may be Levied upon any one Perſon for the Preachers not declaring his Name and Habitation, and the Act is worded thus; and if the ſaid Preacher or Teacher ſo convicted, be a ſtranger, and his Name and Habitation not known, or is fled and cannot be found, or in the Judgment of the Juſtice, Juſtices or chief Magiſtrate, before whom he ſhall be convicted, ſhall be thought unable to pay the Sum, the ſaid
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109781:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Juſtice, Juſtices, or chief Margiſtrate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, are hereby impowered and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to Levy the ſame by Warrant as aforeſaid, upon the Goods and Chattels of any ſuch Perſons, who ſhall be preſent at the ſaid Conventicle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now had the word Perſons been in the ſingular number, it had made ſomething to the purpoſe; but <hi>Francis,</hi> thy covering I do think will be too ſcant to cover thy deceit, and I do believe it had been better for thee every way, that thou hadſt not ſo earneſtly hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after <hi>S. C</hi>'s. 15 <hi>l.</hi> But ſince thou haſt gone ſo far in it, there is little hopes of any better Service in thy miſcarriages, then that others may thereby beware that they enter not into the like Temptations, and ſo be caught in the ſame Snare.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſhua Bangs.</signed>
               <dateline>At <hi>Hallywell-Row</hi> in <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> 
                  <date>the 13th of the 12th M. 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="certificate">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:109781:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edward Swantons</hi> Certificate of <hi>F. B</hi>'s. having 5 <hi>l.</hi> of the 15 <hi>l.</hi> Fine repayed Him by the Juſtice.</head>
            <p>THis may Certifie all whom it may concern, that whereas <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> of <hi>Mildenhall</hi> in the ſaid County, Avereth that he Paid 15 Pounds or above for his being preſent at a Conventicle or Meeting in <hi>Laken-Heath,</hi> ſome years laſt paſt, which I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be true, but I do affirm, that Five Pounds of the aforeſaid Sum was Allowed and paid unto him back again by Juſtice <hi>Shelly,</hi> or his order (as the ſaid Mr. <hi>Shelly</hi> Informed <hi>Me,</hi>) and this I am ready to Teſtifie upon Oath at any time when by Lawful Authority thereto called:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under my hand <date>this Ninteenth day of <hi>January,</hi> Anno Dom. 1682.</date> 
                  <hi>Laken-Heath</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Edward Swanton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> By this Certificate thou mayeſt ſee <hi>Fran. Bugg</hi> hath retained Five pound to himſelf, and <hi>Edw. Swanton</hi> ſays, if he be ſo confident as to deny it, notwithſtanding what he hath herein given forth, he can produce more if need require, to Aſſertain the truth of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:109781:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſhort Reply to <hi>Francis Bugg's</hi> Foul Slanders caſt upon me and his Couſin <hi>George Smith,</hi> in his Book called the <hi>Painted Harlot Stripped and Whipped. Printed 1683.</hi> Wherein not only his <hi>Folly,</hi> but alſo his bitter <hi>Envy,</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered againſt us and others, who never gave him juſt cauſe ſo Maliciouſly to Abuſe us.</head>
            <p>Firſt, I take Notice of <hi>F. B</hi>'s ſaying, that <hi>I Reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Controverſie which was formerly between him G. S.</hi> and my ſelf, after (ſaith he) <hi>It was ended by Friends</hi> at Hadenham, <hi>the Firſt of the</hi> 10th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1680. Which ſaying of his is falſe, and his own Letter, Dated <hi>Auguſt</hi> 10th 1682. plainly proves the contrary, and gives him the Lye; For before he ſent me that Letter, nor ſome time after, I never wrote a word to him nor any other Man from the time of that <hi>Hadenham</hi> Meeting, whereby to ſtir up any thing of that Nature, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was I willing to have meddled with it any more, and that he himſelf very well knew, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, he thus ſaith; for when he ſent me that Letter Dated as before, wherein he did not only <hi>Invite me to begin again</hi> about that Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie which he ſaid was ended; but in that Letter uſed many <hi>Scurrillous words,</hi> whereby to <hi>Provoke me</hi> and <hi>G. S.</hi> thereunto, as it plainly appeared thereby when we came to ſee it; but I underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it came from him, I never opened it, but ſent it him back again, not being willing to concern my ſelf in any Controverſie, which was alſo the cauſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109781:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>I did not meddle to anſwer any part of his former Book, Intituled <hi>De Chriſtiana Liberiate,</hi> wherein he much abuſed me with the reſt of Friends, in this Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> and although I refuſed to meddle with his Book and Letter, whereby he might have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be Quarrelling with me again, he ſent the ſecond Letter to <hi>London</hi> to Friends there that he had ſent to me, and a Copy alſo thereof to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> to <hi>A. D.</hi> and complained to her that he had ſent me the like, and I would not Read it, who wrote to me and in her Letter, ſaid, I did well in not opening <hi>F. Bs.</hi> Letter, whereby to enter into farther Controverſie with him; and yet he is ſo impudent as to ſay in this Idle Ridiculous work of his, <hi>That it was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I that Revived the Controverſie again,</hi> which is as abſolutely falſe, as Truth is Truth. But after he had thus ſent his malicious Letter about, and it came from <hi>London,</hi> whither he had ſent it, wherein he had Reviled me and his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi> again, ſo that his hard charge againſt us for breaking Covenant falls upon himſelf with his Slanderous comparing of us to <hi>Berket</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, which will return upon his own Head, for he broke the agreement made between him and the Meeting, and not I nor <hi>G. S.</hi> for altho I was not there, neither knew any thing of it until ſome Friends came from the Meeting and told me what was done, yet for Peace ſake, and out of reſpect I had to the Meeting, I was willing to condeſcend to it, and did abide by it until he broke it, but when came to ſee and hear how he had abuſed us again, both it City and Country, we did then reſolve to give a true Narrative of the buſineſs, as it truly was, and leave it to People to judge, <hi>Whether he hath wronged us, or we him;</hi> Seeing his reſtleſs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109781:37"/>Spirit would not let him be at quiet, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly we did write to him to give him account thereof, as by the Narrative doth more fully appear.</p>
            <p>The next paſſage I take Notice of, is, how <hi>F. B.</hi> hath in effect Confeſſed himſelf, Guilty of going beyond his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi> in getting the Mony aforeſaid, as by his own Tongue and Pen he hath here Confeſt, for ſays <hi>F. B.</hi> in Page 35, (Treating about the Mony he got of <hi>G. S.</hi>) <hi>He pretended Trouble or elſe he was really Troubled in that he thought</hi> all <hi>I aimed at was,</hi> a bare tender, <hi>and upon that, without any other terms, would have returned it.</hi> Theſe words of <hi>F. Bs.</hi> gives juſt cauſe to believe that he betrayed him by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty out of his Mony, as <hi>G. S.</hi> hath given ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or elſe why ſhould <hi>F. B.</hi> himſelf ſay, (who is ſeldom wanting to make a deceitful cover, for this his work of Darkneſs) <hi>G. S. might think than all he intended in having the Mony all Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was but a bare</hi> Tender, <hi>and that he would have returned it again:</hi> which ſaying of <hi>F. Bs.</hi> gives ground to believe that <hi>G. S.</hi> had ſome cauſe ſo to think, from ſomething that <hi>F. B.</hi> had ſpoke or promiſed to <hi>G. S.</hi> before he tendered him the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as <hi>G. S.</hi> hath declared, for he is not ſo weak a Man as to think of having all the Mony returned again, without ſome Grounds for it. But however, they that ſhall ſay, <hi>That</hi> F. B. <hi>got this Mony Frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently, or by over-teaching, or going beyond his near Kinſman,</hi> them he ſeems to be much offended with, accounting <hi>they Grate much upon his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> But let <hi>F. B.</hi> give his getting the Money what Name he pleaſe, I know it is a way that is not uſed by ſuch as are accounted Honeſt Morral-Men,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109781:38"/>ſetting Chriſtianity aſide; which brings Men not only to Act and Speak juſtly, uprightly, and truly, and to walk inoffenſively both towards God and Men, but alſo Patiently to ſuffer Injuries, and to do good againſt Evil, however 'tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in its place to do juſtly between Man and Man, which <hi>F. B.</hi> in this matter hath fallen farr ſhort of, as doth yet farther appear from his own words, as may be ſeen in page 36, his words are theſe, (Speaking about the ſaid Money, he got of his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi>) <hi>I did proffer</hi> (ſaith he) to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn 7 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s. which I had more then</hi> G. S. <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily proffered me,</hi> (Note, that <hi>F.Bs.</hi> offer of returning the ſaid 7 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> was about three years after he had Received it of his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi> and that not until he was ſeverely Reproved for his unfair dealings by Friends; and farther, he did not offer the Mony as Repenting him for his ſo unjuſtly obtaining it) Therefore it may be very well queſtioned how <hi>F. B.</hi> came by the ſaid 7 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>s.</hi> Seeing he ſays himſelf that <hi>G. S. Did not Voluntarily proffer it him,</hi> then does it not follow, that without queſtion <hi>G. S.</hi> tendred him the whole, thinking thereby to have pleaſed him in his wilful humour, and thinking as <hi>F. B.</hi> himſelf ſaith; <hi>He would have been pleaſed with a bare Formal Tender thereof, and ſo have returned the whole 15 <hi>l.</hi> again;</hi> but ſeeing <hi>F. B.</hi> did not return it all again, according as he ſays, <hi>G. S.</hi> his thoughts might be that he would, yet to keep the other half alſo, which was by him never <hi>Volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> proffered him, let <hi>F. B.</hi> make what covers and excuſes he can for himſelf, People that know what it is to Live uprightly, and to deal juſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Man and Man, will account this Deed of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109781:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>F. Bs.</hi> to Spring from a Covetous and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching-Mind, and a Deed that does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch a Man as would be accounted a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Quaker,</hi> and one that hath taken upon him lately to complain of others, more Honeſt and Juſt then himſelf, as appears; But it had been well for <hi>F. B.</hi> if he had better ſpent this time. which he now ſpends, in Silly, Scornful, Scribling and Printing againſt his Ancient Friends, and ſuch whom he uſed to ſpeak very well off before, the Enemy of his Soul thus filled him with Envy; It had been better (I ſay) for him to have waited upon God in Humility, to have ſeen firſt the Beam caſt out of his own Eye (as Chriſt ſaith) before he had ſo much concerned himſelf to pull the Mote out of anothers Eye. But now mark, after <hi>F. B.</hi> had thus got this Mony of his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi> the the next thing he endeavoured to do, was to quiet him that he might keep it, and to that end he firſt gave him a paper, as he himſelf ſaith, for me to ſign, which he ſaid, <hi>If I would Sign he would Return all the Mony again;</hi> But <hi>G. S.</hi> knowing that he had nothing to do with papers, but the Mony, which he had made him a tender of, ſeeing he never ſpake of any ſuch paper before the Money was tendred, Slighted the paper, but preſt-hard upon him for the Money again, (as more at large ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Narrative) that he might carry and Repay the 10 <hi>l.</hi> again to the Perſon of whom it was borrowed; But <hi>F. B.</hi> would not part with the Money, but be thought himſelf of another way, to try Salve the Sore which he had made in his Couſins mind, by keeping the ſaid Money from him, as himſelf ſaith (in Page the 35 of his Book) to his Couſin <hi>G. S.</hi> after he had got the ſaid 15 <hi>l.</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:109781:39"/>his words are theſe, <hi>However to comfort him, I told him that Samuell had 10 <hi>l.</hi> lately ſent him from</hi> London; <hi>and that he had taken</hi> 40 s. <hi>at one place when he went into Scotland, towards his charges, and</hi> 3 l. <hi>at another place, on the account of his Miniſtry, and ſo Couſin ſaid I, there is no fear but Samuel will made whole.</hi> Theſe are <hi>F. Bs.</hi> own words to <hi>G. S.</hi> (as he himſelf ſaith) But this will prove a Deceitful Cure and Cover as hereafter will appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>F. B.</hi> in ſome other places in his Book, accounts this as a great Evil, (he taking it for granted that I received this Mony he upbraids me with) or elſe why is it ſo often ſpoken of in his Book, but it is not a greater Evil in him, to uſe it as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to perſwade <hi>G. S.</hi> to let him alone quietly with this 15 <hi>l.</hi> he ſo unfeignedly obtained from him, that ſo he might have the benefit of this Money which he blames me for Receiving, which 15 <hi>l.</hi> he had thus obtained of <hi>G. S.</hi> he never offered Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily but one half of it, then it muſt needs follow that he got the other half by Craft, and kept it againſt <hi>G. S.</hi> his Mind, which is doubtleſs a great Evil in the ſight of God, and a juſt cauſe of the breach of Friendſhip and humane Society betwixt Man and Man, thus to do.</p>
            <p>And whereas in page 46 <hi>F. B.</hi> ſpeaks ſomething there as if <hi>R. S.</hi> with ſome other Friends hath given it as their Judgement <hi>that S. Cs. Wife betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed G. S. about this Money,</hi> which thing cannot ſtand with Truth nor found Reaſon, for let it be conſidered whether it can be underſtood or believed by any Man to be as he ſaith, ſeeing <hi>F. B.</hi> was the Man that thus obtained the Money of <hi>G. S.</hi> as is before mentioned: and <hi>S. C.</hi> and his Wife
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109781:39"/>did freely and willingly repay the aforeſaid <hi>G. S.</hi> the whole 15 <hi>l.</hi> again, and beſides, when it was debated in that Monthly Meeting, it will appear that <hi>R. S.</hi> was not of that mind then (neither was it ever the Judgment of the Monthly or Quarterly Meeting that it was <hi>S. C's.</hi> Wife betrayed <hi>G. S.</hi> but on the contrary, that <hi>F. B.</hi> was the betrayer of <hi>G. S.</hi> for at the ſaid Monthly Meeting <hi>B. S.</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out to Friends about the time of the Record making to know where there was a Man in the Meeting that would ſay that <hi>Francis</hi> had right to that Money, and that he came Honeſtly by it? And indeed was the very Man that was Zealous againſt <hi>F. B.</hi> in that Meeting, which cauſed <hi>F. B.</hi> to fall out with him in the Meeting, and reprove the ſaid <hi>R. S.</hi> for being the cauſe of his being ſo far Ingaged in that concern, and inſtanced ſome particulars.</p>
            <p>And again, whereas <hi>F. B.</hi> makes no ſmall ſtirr (in this Slanderous peice of confuſion) about my being grown: Rich with Preaching, who ſays I was ſo Poor that I could ſcatced pay my Debts, both which I return back upon him again as Lyes and De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amation, but his Tongue is no Slander, for firſt I never was ſo Poore as not able to pay my Debts, but have always paid every Man his juſt due, ſince I knew what it was to deal and Trade in the World, neither was any Man ever burthened with my Debts, nor yet paid one penny for me, which thoſe that I have dealt with can witneſs for me; But now how I came to be ſo Rich, as he pretends it was or is by <hi>Making advantage of People by my Preaching,</hi> of which <hi>F. B.</hi> hath threatned long to make a diſcovery of me and my Brethren. But I have told him,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109781:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>he might do his worſt,</hi> for I have both Faith and a good Conſcience on my ſide, and alſo Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the Hearts of Honeſt Friends, where I have Laboured and Travelled, <hi>That I have not ſought my ſelf, nor to inrich my ſelf, by any thing of this, But have truly preferred the good of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Souls, before my own outward benefit,</hi> and this many can Witneſs to the Truth of what I ſay: but now <hi>F. B.</hi> hath brought forth this Monſter, what does he charge me with? <hi>With being Rich with Preaching;</hi> But I do not know what Ground any have to believe that by any thing that he hath brought to Light, except ſuch as are as full of Envy as himſelf, who if any ſuch as he ſays it, it is enough for him to believe it; but let any Rational Man conſider what he tells People of that I have Received, for near theſe 20 years he hath known me, and I perceive hath been watching over me with an Evil Eye for ſome time. And what is it that he ſays of the Sums of Money I have Received in this time, whereby (he ſays) I am made a Rich-Man? Why, ſays he, <hi>Three Sums of Money, which in all amounts to</hi> 15 l. but let it alſo be conſidered, that if I had Received all the three Sums as <hi>F. B.</hi> ſays, (which I ſays, <hi>I had not;</hi> let him prove it if he can) how much have I left me, towards making me a Rich-Man, when I had paid <hi>G. S.</hi> the 15 <hi>l.</hi> which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes he had of him, and which I paid again, altho no more then half of it was voluntarily proffered him by <hi>G. S.</hi> might not <hi>F. B.</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be aſhamed, I am ſure he would (if he were a tender Hearted Man and feared God) of this his wicked work, who ſometimes hath called me <hi>Penſioner,</hi> and compares me to be like to the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109781:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>hireling Prieſts, who are known to Preach for Money, either by the year, or ſo much a Sermon, as they can get, and now tells the World of my Receiving 15 <hi>l.</hi> for near 20 years, for ſuffering Travelling (as he pretends) and Preaching: might not People have thought that I have had ſome great Salary (by ſuch his Inſinuations) for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for which I do ſay, that I never took pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more nor leſs, directly or indirectly in my Life, but am wholly clear of his Malicious and Scandalous thing, both in the ſight of God and Honeſt People, neither can <hi>F. B.</hi> prove it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he hath ſo Reproachfully Inſinuated it againſt me, expect he or any other Man will or can account that the 3 <hi>l.</hi> I Received as part of the 20 <hi>l.</hi> given by the laſt Will and Teſtament of <hi>J. M.</hi> of <hi>Whitleſea-Coles,</hi> which I Received with other Friends, according to the intent and deſire of the Giver, which no Impartial and unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Perſon will blame me for, but ſuch as are Levened with the Spirit of Envy, as <hi>F. B.</hi> hath Manifeſted himſelf to be both againſt me and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. He ſays he was our Book-Keeper ſo many years, and thereby had opportunity to know what was then done amongſt us, but he to make the ſaid 15 <hi>l.</hi> ſeem as big as he can, he hath brought it up ſeveral times in his Book, ſometimes he ſays I Received it as a Preacher, ſometimes as a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer and as a Traveller; but ſtill it is all but 15 <hi>l.</hi> ſome of which I never had.</p>
            <p>Again he is hinting in an interlined Note, <hi>Page</hi> 40. as if I knew, <hi>that the Widow</hi> Moor, <hi>nigh</hi> Biſhop-Gate London, <hi>hath understood what he means, who</hi> (ſays he) <hi>was conſtrained to break up Houſe,</hi> being (as he inſinuates) ſo much oppreſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109781:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>by me, and ſuch as I am, as he hath declared, which I know nothing of that ſhe would give over Houſe-keeping upon any ſuch Account, neither was I burdenſome to her, but if I would have accepted it, (as ſhe deſired of me) I might have been there to have Lodged when I refuſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did I ever here that ſhe or any related to her complain of any ſuch oppreſſion. Well, but <hi>F. B.</hi> does not leave here, for in <hi>Page</hi> 54. he ſays, <hi>If all thy ſufferings be attended with ſuch a plentiful reward, I do not know but that ſufferings may be as beneficial to thee as of Old they were to Biſhop</hi> Worren. And for Inſtance, (he ſaith) <hi>It hath been ſaid that in</hi> Ely <hi>Priſon by Treat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and otherwiſe, they believe thou faireſt as well as ſome Perſons of much Higher Degree.</hi> But if this be all thou haſt to ſay about thy Fooliſhly comparing me to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Worren</hi> in his ſufferings, I ſay it was well the Man in the time of his confinement, found Friends in the midſt of his Enemies, to take care of him, and ſhew kindneſs to him, and I praiſe the Lord, ſo have I in Meaſure, in the time of my cloſe confinement, although it be to my Enemies grief, which thou haſt appeared to be none of the Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, who has been abuſing me from time to time, in the time of my ſufferings, by which thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts not only thy envy againſt me, but ſeemeſt to be troubled that any Loves me, but thou muſt run thy race, and make thy folly manifeſt to all, till the Lord put a Hook in thy Noſtrills before thou wilt be quiet, and thou maieſt be aſhamed, Nay, I am ſure thou wouldeſt, if Envy did not Blind thee, how the Devil befools thee in thy undertakeings, to make a Noiſe about my being grown Rich with Preaching, and now wanting
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109781:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>proof againſt me, makes thy appeal to my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and to the Pariſh Prieſt, whether they have got ſo much as I have, but what if ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours have gotten much more in theſe 30 years time that I have kept Houſe, as ſome of them have done, and ſome leſs, and others ſpent what they have, what's that to the proof of thy change againſt me? And I have told thee before, I have nothing but what I came honeſtly and juſtly by, neither haſt thou proved the contrary, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there's none have cauſe to believe thee, nor will, that are not Learned with that Spirit of Envy that thou art in, whoſe reproaches are little to me, knowing it is the Portion of them that fear God to go through good report, and evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, as the Servants of God did before me.</p>
            <p>Now whereas <hi>F. B.</hi> makes a great ſtirr about a Lawyer medling in my Caſe, and calls me <hi>his Client,</hi> I do ſay, I never ſpoke or writ, neither directly or indirectly imployed <hi>T. R.</hi> about the ſaid concern, whereof he ſo ſaieth, and if the ſaid <hi>T. R.</hi> did any thing in it, he did it of himſelf, and not by any Order or Advice from me; and that I have told <hi>F. B.</hi> before now, only he is minded to fill up his filthy Book with ſomething, although it doth and will return to his own ſhame. Many things more might be ſpoken unto, to manifeſt his numerous lies and falſhoods, and his wild Airy ſcoffing Spirit againſt my ſelf and many others, which at preſent I paſs by, looking upon it not worth the ſpending time about, nor queſtioning but impartial and unbiaſſed Readers will ſee that its <hi>more Mallice then Matter againſt us,</hi> as one lately told me, who is not of our Society: Neither would I too much Treat him in his Folly, leſt (as the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109781:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>wiſe Man ſaith) I appear like him, neither would I be altogether, ſilent leſt he grows Proud in his own conceit. And having given Account of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action in theſe things before I ſaw his, and now made ſome reply in ſhort, to what I thought moſt needful in this, I ſhall commit my Innocent Cauſe to God and to his juſt witneſs in the Conſciences of all that Reads both his and mine, to Judg in themſelves who is in the wrong, or what cauſe he hath thus to abuſe me. And reſt a Friend to all that love Truth and Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel Cater.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ely Priſon</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 17th <hi>of the</hi> 6th <hi>Month,</hi> 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Now the Controverſie Rightly conſidered, <hi>F. B.</hi> may apply the Title of his Book to himſelf, and his own Mallicious Scornful Spirit.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>George Smith's</hi> return to <hi>F. B.</hi>'s Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous report of him in his Book Intituled, <hi>The painted Harlot,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>WHereas I have lately ſeen the ſaid Book put forth by my Coſin <hi>F. B.</hi> wherein he hath Treated me as uncivilly, as he got the Mony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of me unfairly: For he hath taken two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages out of a Letter of mine which I formerly ſent him in Anſwer to one he ſent me, after he had the Mony, wherein I much blamed him for his unjuſt and unfair dealings with me about the 15 Pounds as I have given Account of. And now I
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109781:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>find he hath taken out of that large Letter (which contained almoſt three ſides of a Sheet of Paper) only two paſſages barely from what went before and followeth after, and which is explanatory to that which he hath recited, whereby his unfair and Falacious dealing is manifeſt, for by that way he makes my Letter ſeemingly ſpeak what he would have it, and not what I intended, and is thereby apparent; and when he had done ſo, then he para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſes upon it, and tells what lies he pleaſes, to abuſe me. But God that knoweth the Secrets of all Hearts, knows how much he hath belied and abuſed me, and <hi>S. C.</hi> and his Wife thereby, in Page 38. He brings me in ſpeaking in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to him in this manner, <hi>viz, I am ingaged to give an Account of this buſineſs, without I would hear the loſs of all the 15 Pounds aforeſaid. And again, that I am neceſſitated now to give ſuch a report left the Parties concerned ſhould think I was too much biaſſed in joyning with thee.</hi> Thus farr he hath Quoted me, by which two Paſſages he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends as if I told <hi>S. C.</hi> and his Wife ſome falſe ſtory of him to get my Mony again; which is altogether falſe, and nothing true in it, neither will my words bare ſuch a conſtruction in my Letter as he makes of them, if they be Read as I have ſet them down, for his conſtruction is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intent of my mind, for my mind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is to ſpeak plainly and truly how he got the Mony of me, as may be ſeen in my Letter, and for that end, that the Truth may be known, I have hereunto annexed that part of my Letter, out of which he pretends to have taken them words, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out what made not for his turn, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to all that reads it. The other large part I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109781:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>leave out for Brevity ſake, and which I find not medled with in his ſaid Book.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Theſe are the Words of the Letter <hi>Verbatim,</hi> viz.</head>
                  <p>OH Coſin, thy State is to be La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, I deſire the Lord may give thee a true ſight of thy ſins, leaſt that Scripture be fulfilled upon thee, where the Apoſtle ſays, the Love of Mony is the Root of all Evil; whilſt ſome have covered after it, they have Erred from the Faith, and have Pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced themſelves with many ſorrows, and fallen into many dangerous and hurtfull Luſts, thou ſeems to be much offended becauſe I ſpoke of thy unjuſt dealings by me in this matter, indeed thou mayeſt very well be aſhamed to hear, that one ſo nearly related to thee as I am, and have had ſo much Love for thee as I have had, ſhould
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109781:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>have <hi>ſo juſt a cauſe as thou haſt given me,</hi> to give <hi>ſuch a Report of thee</hi> as I am neceſſitated now to do for the <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my own Innocency,</hi> that ſo the Parties concerned, nor no others that hears of it, may think that I was too much biaſſed in joyning with thee in this matter, ſo that I am ingaged to give an Account of the buſineſs <hi>as it is,</hi> without I would bare the loſs of all this Mony, <hi>to cover thy Deceit,</hi> and how unreaſonable that is, I leave it to the honeſt to Judge, for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that the buſineſs does not end in thee and I, and therefore it muſt be known, and beſides I do not find Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in my ſelf to cover <hi>ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful dealings as thou haſt uſed in this matter,</hi> I perceive that thou hadſt been contented that I ſhould have held my Tongue to <hi>have covered thee,</hi> and bore the Mony my ſelf for my good will. So no more at preſent but my hearty deſire that thou may truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109781:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>and forſake all ſuch Actions as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>re.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>And ſo Remain thy Kinſman</hi> George Smith.</signed>
                     <dateline>Littleport <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 22d. <hi>of the</hi> 8th <hi>Month,</hi> 1679.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>WHereas <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> hath falſly accuſed <hi>Samuel Cater, &amp;c.</hi> with <hi>Growing ſo Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive (when going on Truths Errand) that the Widdows ſubstance is devoured, that ſome have been Conſtrained to Break up Houſe.</hi> For which he Quotes, our Deceaſed Mother, thus, <hi>viz.</hi> Sam. Cater <hi>knows, that the Widow</hi> More <hi>at the Seven Stars nigh</hi> Biſhops gate London, <hi>hath understood what I mean,</hi> now we her two Sons, (one of us living with her, when ſhe Lived there,) do affirm this to be an abuſive Forgery, and foul Defamation and Scandal, for we know of no ſuch thing of our Deceaſed Mother, nor never did hear ſo much as the leaſt complaint thereof from her, and we are certain ſhe did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leave off Shop upon any ſuch Account, as.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Witnes our Hands,</hi> John <hi>and</hi> Joſeph Moor.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 30th <hi>of the</hi> 6th <hi>Month,</hi> 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109781:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:109781:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertiſement</head>
            <p>THere is now in the PRESS a Book, Entituled, <hi>The Liberty of an Apoſtate Conſcience: being a plain Narrative of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie long depending Between</hi> Francis Bugg <hi>on the one part, and</hi> Samuel Cater <hi>and</hi> George Smith <hi>on the other part: whereby</hi> F. Bugg's Liberty of Conſcience <hi>is proved not only</hi> Unchriſtian, <hi>but</hi> Immoral <hi>and</hi> Injurious.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
